GOOD AFTERNOON WELCOME TO THE DECEMBER 9TH 2025 REGULAR
MEETING OF THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL?
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. >> SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN
PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR CHEN CHAN PRESENT SUPERVISOR DORSEY
DORSEY PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER PRESENT
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN
PRESENT MANDEL MEN PRESENT SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
PRESENT SUPERVISOR SADR SADR PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL
SHERRELL PRESENT SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON PRESENT
AND SUPERVISOR HUANG WONG NOT PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT YOU HAVE
A QUORUM. >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT
WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL HOMELAND OF THE ROMITA ALONI
WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL INHABITANTS OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO PENINSULA. AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF
THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE
ROMITA ALONE WE HAVE NEVER CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR
RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS
WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL
TERRITORY. >> AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT
WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR
TRADITIONAL HOMELAND. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS, ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE
ROMITA ALONI COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR SOVEREIGN
RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES. COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME
IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF ALLEGIANCE?
I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG OF THE UNITED STATES TO THE
REPUBLIC FOR WHICH IT STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD
INDIVISIBLE WITH LIBERTY. >> ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD I
WANT TO THANK AND ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT US OF GOV TV TODAY
THAT IS PARTICULARLY EUGENE LABBADIA.
THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR MEETINGS AND MAKE TRANSCRIPTS
AVAILABLE TO THE PUBLIC ONLINE .
>> MADAM CLERK DO YOU HAVE ANY COMMUNICATIONS?
YES MR. PRESIDENT. OUR OFFICES IN RECEIPT OF A
MEMO FROM SUPERVISOR ALAN HUANG REQUESTING TO BE EXCUSED FROM
THE BOARD MEETING UNTIL HIS ARRIVAL TO THE CHAMBER.
GREAT. COLLEAGUES, WE HAVE A REQUEST
FROM SUPERVISOR WONG TO BE EXCUSED.
CAN I GET A MOTION MOVED BY CHEN AND SECONDED BY SÖDER.
MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MOTION TO
EXCUSE SUPERVISOR WONG UNTIL HIS ARRIVAL TO THE CHAMBER.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I
MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUTER SADR
I SUPERVISOR CHERYL SHERRELL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER
I THERE ARE TEN EYES THE MOTION PASSES AND SUPERVISOR WONG IS
EXCUSED MADAM CLERK. >> WAS THAT IT FOR YOUR
COMMUNICATIONS? I WILL JUST STATE THAT IF YOU
NEED TO MAKE A REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION TO A FUTURE
MEETING UNDER THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES ACT OR IF YOU
NEED TO REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE PLEASE CONTACT THE
CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE.
YOU CAN CALL THE NUMBER (415) 554-5184.
>> THANK YOU. UH, LET'S GO TO OUR MEETING
MINUTES. >> APPROVAL OF THE OCTOBER 21ST
2025 REGULAR BOARD MEETING MINUTES AND THE NOVEMBER 3RD,
2025 SPECIAL MEETING MINUTES AT THE LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION
COMMITTEE MEETING WHICH CONSTITUTED A QUORUM OF THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND I HAVE A MOTION TO APPROVE THE MINUTES
AS PRESENTED AND MOVED BY FIELDER SECONDED BY MELGAR.
>> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR
RANDLEMAN I RANDLEMAN EYES SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR EYES
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT
AS PRESENTED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO THE CONSENT AGENDA ITEMS
ONE THROUGH EIGHT ITEMS ONE THROUGH EIGHT ARE ON CONSENT.
THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED TO BE ROUTINE.
IF A MEMBER OBJECTS AN ITEM MAY BE REMOVED AND CONSIDERED
SEPARATELY. >> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON
ITEMS ONE THROUGH EIGHT SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN HI MANDOLIN I'M SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I'M
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED OR ORDINANCES
ARE FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL OUR NEXT WHERE ARE
WE? >> SORRY PLEASE CALL ITEM NINE
ITEM NINE THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO APPROPRIATE 4.5 MILLION OF
STATE COST REIMBURSEMENT REVENUE TO THE DEPARTMENT OF
ELECTIONS TO SUPPORT COSTS ASSOCIATED WITH THE STATEWIDE
NOVEMBER 2025 SPECIAL ELECTION IN FISCAL YEAR 2025 AND 2026
AND SPECIFICALLY FOR THE STATE REIMBURSEMENT SHARE OF
4,178,500. THIS ITEM REQUIRES A TWO THIRDS
THRESHOLD OR AT LEAST EIGHT VOTES OF ALL MEMBERS OF THE
BOARD TO APPROVE THIS APPROPRIATION ORDINANCE FOR
FINAL PASSAGE PURSUANT TO TURN OF SECTION 3.113 SUBSIDY AND I
THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
I MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM TEN.
>> ITEM TEN THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AUTHORIZE
SETTLEMENT OF THE LAWSUIT FILED BY TOMMY O.
JOHNSON BY AND THROUGH HIS ATTORNEY.
IN FACT REV DORIS WHITE AND JOHN DOE BY AND THROUGH HIS
CONSERVATOR THOMAS O'CONNOR ON BEHALF OF THEMSELVES AND ALL
OTHERS SIMILARLY SITUATED AGAINST THE CITY FOR
APPROXIMATELY 5.8 MILLION. THIS LAWSUIT INVOLVES CLAIMS OF
ELDER DEPENDENT ADULT ABUSE, INVASION OF PRIVACY, NEGLIGENCE
AND VIOLATIONS OF PATIENTS RIGHTS BROUGHT OVER BY 700
FORMER AND CURRENT RESIDENTS OF LAGUNA HONDA HOSPITAL.
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS FINALLY PASSED. MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS
11 THROUGH 14 TOGETHER ITEMS 11 THROUGH 14 ARE THREE ORDINANCES
AND A RESOLUTION THAT COMPRISED THE FAMILY ZONING PLAN.
ITEM 11 THIS ORDINANCE AMENDS THE GENERAL PLAN TO REVISE THE
URBAN DESIGN ELEMENT COMMERCE AND INDUSTRY ELEMENT
TRANSPORTATION ELEMENT THE BALBOA PARK STATION AREA PLAN,
THE GLEN PARK COMMUNITY PLAN, THE MARKET AND OCTAVIA AREA
PLAN THE NORTHEASTERN WATERFRONT PLAN THE VAN NESS
AVENUE AREA PLAN THE WESTERN SOMA AREA PLAN THE WESTERN
SHORELINE AREA PLAN THE DOWNTOWN AREA PLAN AND LAND USE
INDEX TO IMPLEMENT THE FAMILY HOUSING ZONING PROGRAM BY
ADJUSTING GUIDELINES REGARDING BUILDING HEIGHTS DENSITY DESIGN
AND OTHER MATTERS TO AMEND THE CITY'S LOCAL COASTAL PROGRAM
AND TO MAKE OTHER APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
ITEM 12 THIS ORDINANCE AMENDS THE ZONING MAP TO IMPLEMENT THE
FAMILY ZONING PLAN BY AMENDING THE ZONING USE DISTRICT MAPS TO
RECLASSIFY CERTAIN PROPERTIES TO AMEND THE HEIGHT AND BULK
MAP TO RECLASSIFY PROPERTIES TO CHANGE THE HEIGHT LIMITS ON
CERTAIN LOTS AND DESIGNATING VARIOUS PARCELS TO BE INCLUDED
IN THE SFM TO STUDY TO AMEND THE LOCAL COASTAL PROGRAM TO
RECLASSIFY CERTAIN PROPERTIES AND TO DESIGNATE ONE PARCEL AS
PART OF THE SFM TO STUDY AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
ITEM 13 THIS ORDINANCE AMENDS THE PLANNING CODE TO CREATE THE
HOUSING CHOICE SAN FRANCISCO PROGRAM TO MODIFY HEIGHT
AND BULK LIMITS TO REQUIRE ONLY BUILDINGS TALLER THAN 85FT
IN CERTAIN DISTRICTS TO REDUCE GROUND LEVEL WIND CURRENTS TO
CREATE THE RESIDENTIAL TRANSIT ORIENTED COMMERCIAL DISTRICT
THE AUTO DASH C TO IMPLEMENT THE METROPOLITAN TRANSPORTS
ATION COMMISSION'S TRANSIT ORIENTED COMMUNITIES POLICY TO
REVISE OFF STREET PARKING AND CURB CUT OBLIGATION
CITYWIDE TO CREATE THE SFM TO STUDY PERMIT BUSINESSES
DISPLACED BY NEW CONSTRUCTION TO RELOCATE WITHOUT A
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION AND REDUCE USABLE OPEN SPACE
AND BICYCLE PARKING REQUIREMENTS FOR SENIOR HOUSING
TO AMEND THE BUSINESS AND TAX REGULATIONS CODE REGARDING THE
BOARD OF APPEALS REVIEW OF PERMITS TO AMEND THE LOCAL
COASTAL PROGRAM TO IMPLEMENT THE HOUSING CHOICE FOR SAN
FRANCISCO PROGRAM AND TO MAKE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS AND FOR
ITEM 14 THIS RESOLUTION REQUIRES THE TRANSMISSION TO
THE CALIFORNIA COASTAL COMMISSION FOR REVIEW
AND CERTIFICATION AND AMENDMENT TO THE IMPLEMENTATION PROGRAM
AND LAND USE PLAN OF THE CITY'S CERTIFIED LOCAL COASTAL PROGRAM
TO IMPLEMENT THE FAMILY ZONING PLAN AND TO AFFIRM THE SEQUENT
DETERMINATION. >> MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS 11 THROUGH 14?
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUDER
SAUDER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WONTON
MOULTON NO SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER
NO. THERE ARE SIX EYES AND FOUR NOS
WITH SUPERVISORS WALTON CHIN CHIN AND FIELDER VOTING NO THE
ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY PASSED AND THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 15 ITEM 15 THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE BUILDING CODE TO REVISE THE TIMING OF
EXPIRATION OF CERTAIN BUILDING PERMITS AND BUILDING PERMIT
APPLICATION FEES AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 15.
>> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
GENTLEMEN. I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO THERE ARE EIGHT EYES
AND THREE EXCUSE ME THERE ARE SEVEN EYES AND THREE NOSE WITH
SUPERVISORS CHIN CHIN AND FIELDER VOTING NO WE NEED
TO RE THERE'S A MOTION TO RESCIND THE VOTE MADE BY
SUPERVISOR WALTON AND SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR CHAN AND CAN WE
TAKE THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION WE CAN TAKE THAT WAS GREAT.
AND CAN YOU CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 15 ON ITEM 15 SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN I MANDOLIN I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON NO
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER
NO. THERE ARE SIX EYES AND FOUR
NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS WALTON CHAN CHIN AND FIELDER VOTING
NO. >> THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON
FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 16 ITEM
16 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PLANNING CODE TO
ALLOW THE CITY TO WAIVE THE INCLUSIONARY HOUSING FEE
AND OTHER REQUIREMENTS IN CERTAIN RESIDENTIAL
AND NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL DISTRICTS OUTSIDE OF THE
PRIORITY EQUITY GEOGRAPHIES SPECIAL USE DISTRICT THE STUDY
IN EXCHANGE FOR A PROJECT SPONSORS AGREEMENT TO SUBJECT
ALL UNITS IN THE PROJECT TO RENT CONTROL AND TO ALLOW
PROJECTS IN CERTAIN RESIDENTIAL AND NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL
DISTRICTS OUTSIDE OF THE PRIORITY EQUITY GEOGRAPHIES.
>> THE STUDY TO COMPLY WITH THE INCLUSIONARY HOUSING ORDINANCE
BY DEDICATING LAND TO THE CITY TO REQUIRE PERIODIC REPORTS TO
THE PLANNING COMMISSION AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION
AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU PRESIDENT.
I JUST WANTED TO ADDRESS THIS ITEM FOR A LITTLE BIT.
IT CAME OUT OF THE LAND USAGE PROTECTION COMMITTEE WITH A
POSITIVE RECOMMENDATION. IT ALSO LEFT THE PLANNING
COMMISSION WITH A UNANIMOUS RECOMMENDATION WITH THE PENDING
REZONING. THIS LEGISLATION PROVIDES MORE
FLEXIBILITY AND OPTIONS FOR DEVELOPERS OUTSIDE OF PRIORITY
EQUITY GEOGRAPHIES TO OPT TO FULFILL THEIR INCLUSIONARY
REQUIREMENTS BY OFFERING RENT CONTROLLED UNITS AND WE WOULD
THUS BE INCREASING TO OUR RENTAL HOUSING STOCK THAT IS
RENT CONTROLLED. RENT CONTROL REMAINS ONE OF THE
MOST IMPORTANT TOOLS FOR OUR LONG TERM STABILITY
AND AFFORDABILITY IN NEIGHBORHOODS GIVEN THE
CURRENT MARKET CONDITIONS, I THINK PROVIDING THESE OPTIONS
IS HELPFUL TO SEE IF WE CAN SPUR MORE RENTAL STOCK
IN NEIGHBORHOODS THAT HAVE HISTORICALLY NOT EMBRACED NEW
HOUSING IN RENTAL HOUSING SUCH AS DISTRICT SEVEN.
AGAIN THIS IS NOT A MANDATE BUT ONLY EXPANDING ADDITIONAL
OPTIONS. WE WORKED WITH AFFORDABLE
HOUSING ORGANIZATIONS TO LIMIT WHERE DEVELOPERS COULD USE THIS
NEW TOOL AND THIS EXEMPTION SO THAT WE CAN FULFILL OUR GOALS
TO SUPPORT MORE RENT CONTROLLED STOCK IN CERTAIN AREAS WHILE
ALSO ENCOURAGING TRADITIONAL BELOW MARKET RATE AFFORDABLE
INCLUSIONARY REQUIREMENTS IN OTHER AREAS.
SO I HOPE I CAN COUNT ON YOUR SUPPORT FOR THIS LEGISLATION.
THANK YOU MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 16.
SUPERVISOR MAHMUD AHMAD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I
MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR I MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL SHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER
I THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 17
AND 18 TOGETHER ITEM 17 AND 18 ARE TO RESOLUTIONS THAT PERTAIN
TO GRANT AGREEMENTS FOR THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS
AND SUPPORTIVE HOUSING. ITEM 17 APPROVES THE THIRD
AMENDMENT TO THE GRANT AGREEMENT BETWEEN EPISCOPAL
COMMUNITY SERVICES AND THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESS
IN SUPPORT OF HOUSING HCA FOR SHELTER SERVICES AT SANCTUARY
SHELTER TO EXTEND THE GRANT TERM BY 24 MONTHS FOR A TOTAL
TERM JULY 1ST 2021 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2028 TO INCREASE THE GRANT
THE AGREEMENT AMOUNT BY 15 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL AMOUNT
OF 41 MILLION AND FOR ITEM 18 THIS RESOLUTION APPROVES THE
THIRD AMENDMENT TO THE GRANT AGREEMENT BETWEEN FELTON
INSTITUTE AND THE H FOR DROP IN CENTER OPERATIONS TO EXTEND
THE GRANT TERM BY 24 MONTHS FROM JUNE 30TH 2026 FOR A NEW
TOTAL TERM OCTOBER 1ST 2022 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2028 AND TO
INCREASE THE AGREEMENT AMOUNT BY 7.1 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL
OF 16.8 MILLION. >> I THINK WE CAN TAKE THESE
ITEMS SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEMS 19 THROUGH 22 TOGETHER ITEMS 19 THROUGH 22 ARE FOR
RESOLUTION FOR RESOLUTION ONES THAT PERTAIN TO PERMANENT
SUPPORTIVE HOUSING FOR THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS
AND SUPPORT OF HOUSING HSC H ITEM 19 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO
AUTHORIZE THE CITY AND COUNTY THROUGH THE DEPARTMENT OF HHS H
TO EXECUTE A STANDARD AGREEMENT WITH THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT
OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT AND TO AND CO
APPLICANT SWORDS TO PLOWSHARES VETERANS RIGHTS ORGANIZATIONS
AND 1035 VETS LLC FOR A TOTAL AWARD OF APPROXIMATELY 39
MILLION UNDER THE HOMEKEY PLUS PROGRAM FOR THE ACQUISITION OF
REAL PROPERTY LOCATED AT 1035 VENICE AVENUE FOR PERMANENT
SUPPORTIVE HOUSING FOR VETERANS AND FOR OPERATING COSTS
AND SUPPORT TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND ANTICIPATED REVENUE
FROM THE CITY'S PORTION OF HOMEKEY PLUS GRANT FUNDS UP TO
3 MILLION FOR THE REHABILITATION OF THE PROPERTY
TO APPROVE AND AUTHORIZE THE CITY TO COMMIT UP TO 8 MILLION
IN REQUIRED MATCHING FUNDS FOR PROPERTY REHABILITATION AND A
MINIMUM OF FIVE YEARS OF OPERATING SUBSIDY.
ADDITIONALLY, THE CITY HAS COMMITTED UP TO 15 YEARS OF
OPERATING SUBSIDIES THROUGH THE CITY'S LOCAL OPERATING SUBSIDY
PROGRAM SUBJECT TO BUDGET APPROPRIATIONS AND TO AUTHORIZE
THE CITY TO ASSUME ANY JOINT AND SEVERAL LIABILITY FOR
EXPENDITURE OF THE HOMEKEY PLUS GRANT UNDER THE STANDARD
AGREEMENT AND TO ADOPT THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS ITEM 20
THIS RESOLUTION APPROVES AND AUTHORIZES A LOAN AND GRANT
AGREEMENT FOR 11 MILLION CONSISTING OF AN 8,000,055 YEAR
MINIMUM TERM LOAN AND A $3 MILLION GRANT WITH 1035 VETS
LLC TO REHABILITATE REAL PROPERTY LOCATED AT 1035 VENICE
AVENUE INTO 124 UNITS OR PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING
FOR VETERANS EXITING HOMELESSNESS AND TO ADOPT THE
APPROPRIATE FINDINGS ITEM 21 THIS RESOLUTION AUTHORIZES THE
CITY AND COUNTY THROUGH THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS
AND SUPPORT OF HOUSING TO EXECUTE A STANDARD AGREEMENT
WITH THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY
DEVELOPMENT AND CODE APPLICANTS 835 TURK LLC AND FIVE KEYS
SCHOOL AND PROGRAMS FOR A TOTAL AWARD OF APPROXIMATELY 17.3
MILLION UNDER THE HOMEKEY PLUS PROGRAM FOR SUPPORT OF
OPERATING COSTS AND UP TO 13.8 MILLION DISBURSED BY HCD AS A
GRANT TO THE CITY FOR REHABILITATION AND ASSOCIATED
RELOCATION COSTS FOR THE REAL PROPERTY LOCATED AT 835 TURK
STREET FOR PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING TO RETROACTIVELY ACCEPT
AND EXPEND ANTICIPATED REVENUE FROM THE CITY'S PORTION OF THE
HOMEKEY PLUS GRANT FUNDS IN AN AMOUNT OF 13.7 MILLION TO
SUPPORT THE REHABILITATION AND ASSOCIATED RELOCATION COSTS
FOR THE PROPERTY FOR COSTS INCURRED FROM MARCH 5TH 2024
THROUGH CDW'S CAPITAL GRANT EXPENDITURE DEADLINE TO APPROVE
AND AUTHORIZE THE CITY TO COMMIT APPROXIMATELY 16.3
MILLION IN REQUIRED MATCHING FUNDS FOR THE REHABILITATION OF
THE PROPERTY AND A MINIMUM OF FIVE YEARS OF OPERATING
SUBSIDIES. ADDITIONALLY, THE CITY HAS
COMMITTED UP TO 15 YEARS OF OPERATING SUBSIDIES THROUGH THE
CITY'S LOCAL OPERATING SUBSIDY PROGRAM SUBJECT TO BUDGET
APPROPRIATIONS AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
AND FOR ITEM 22 THIS RESOLUTION APPROVES AND AUTHORIZES THE
DIRECTOR OF PROPERTY AND THE DEPARTMENT OF HHS TO ENTER INTO
A GROUNDLESS FOR REAL PROPERTY OWNED BY THE CITY LOCATED AT
835 TURK STREET WITH 835 TURK LLC FOR A 55 YEAR LEASE TERM
AND $1 TOTAL RENT IN ORDER TO REHABILITATE AND OPERATE A 100%
PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING 106 UNIT MULTIFAMILY RENTAL
HOUSING DEVELOPMENT AFFORDABLE TO VERY LOW INCOME HOUSEHOLDS
TO APPROVE AND AUTHORIZE THE MAYOR AND THE DIRECTOR OF THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT TO
ENTER INTO A LOAN AND GRANT AGREEMENT WITH A 35 TURK LLC TO
FINANCE THE DEVELOPMENT AND REHABILITATION OF THE
PROJECT WITH A LOAN IN AND $13 MILLION AMOUNT FOR 55 YEARS FOR
A MINIMUM LOAN TERM AND A GRANT OF APPROXIMATE ONLY 13.7
MILLION FROM THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF HOUSING
AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT AND TO ADOPT THE APPROPRIATE
FINDINGS. >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
I THINK WE CAN TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEMS 23 AND 24 TOGETHER.
>> ITEMS 23 AND 24 ARE TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND GRANTS FOR
THE OFFICE OF THE DISTRICT ATTORNEY.
ITEM 23 RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZES THE OFFICE TO ACCEPT
AND EXPEND A $1.1 MILLION GRANT FROM THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT
OF INSURANCE FOR THE WORKER'S COMPENSATION INSURANCE FRAUD
PROGRAM FOR THE GRANT TERM THROUGH JUNE 30TH, 2026
AND ITEM 24 THIS RESOLUTION RETROACTIVELY RETROACTIVELY
AUTHORIZES THE OFFICE TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND AN APPROXIMATE
$347,000 GRANT FROM THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF
INSURANCE FOR THE AUTOMOBILE INSURANCE FRAUD PROGRAM GRANT
TERM THROUGH JUNE 30TH, 2026 AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THESE
ITEMS SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER 25 ITEM 25 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE A TWO
YEAR EXTENSION OF THE AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE RECREATION AND PARK
DEPARTMENT AND ACTIVE NETWORK LLC FOR USE OF THE CITY'S
RECREATION PROGRAMS AND FACILITY RESERVATIONS
BEGINNING DECEMBER 31ST, 2025 FOR A TOTAL TERM THROUGH
DECEMBER 31ST 2027 WITH NO CHANGE TO THE CONTRACT AMOUNT
OF 100,000 ANNUALLY AND TO UPDATE CERTAIN STANDARD
CONTRACTUAL CLAUSES. >> LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS
ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS
26 AND 27 TOGETHER. >> YES ITEMS 26 AND 27 ARE TWO
RESOLUTIONS THAT PERTAIN TO CONTRACT AGREEMENTS FOR THE
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH. ITEM 26 IS THE FIRST AMENDMENT
TO THE AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE CITY AND PRIORITY HEALTH CARE
DISTRIBUTION INC DOING BUSINESS AS CURE A SCRIPT SPECIALTY
DISTRIBUTION FOR THE PROCUREMENT OF SPECIALTY DRUGS
TO EXTEND THE TERM BY FOUR YEARS FROM NOVEMBER 30TH 2026
THROUGH NOVEMBER 30TH 2030 AND TO INCREASE THE AMOUNT BY
89.4 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL OF APPROXIMATELY 98.4 MILLION
AND ITEM 27. THIS RESOLUTION APPROVES THE
SECOND AMENDMENT TO THE AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE CITY
AND D H AND HYDE STREET COMMUNITY SERVICES INC TO
PROVIDE MENTAL HEALTH SERVICES TO EXTEND THE TERM BY TWO YEARS
FROM JUNE 30TH 2026 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2028 AND TO INCREASE
THE AMOUNT BY 11.8 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL AMOUNT OF
APPROXIMATELY 38.8 MILLION AND WE CAN TAKE THESE ITEMS
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER 28 ITEM 28 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE AN
AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE CITY AND H AND THE CALIFORNIA
DEPARTMENT OF SOCIAL SERVICES AND ITS THIRD PARTY
ADMINISTRATOR BDO GOVERNMENT SERVICES LLC HAVING ANTICIPATED
REVENUE OF APPROXIMATELY 7.4 MILLION FOR A PERFORMANCE BASED
PERIOD COMMENCING ON EXECUTION OF THE GRANT AGREEMENT THROUGH
JUNE 30TH 2029. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED.
I DO THINK WE WILL GET TO 29 BUT I WANT TO MAKE SURE WE GET
TO 30 BEFORE WE DO OUR 230 SPECIAL ORDER.
SO MADAM CLERK CAN YOU PLEASE CALL ITEM 30?
>> ITEM 30 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE
CODE TO TO ESTABLISH THE REPARATIONS FUND AND I THINK WE
CAN TAKE THAT SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING AND MADAM CLERK, PLEASE
CALL ON TIME ITEM 29 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE BUSINESS
AND TAX REGULATIONS CODE TO EXTEND THE SUSPENSION OF THE
CANNABIS BUSINESS TAX THROUGH DECEMBER 31ST 2035 AND TO
REMOVE REFERENCES TO THE CANNABIS BUSINESS TAX FROM THE
COMMON ADMINISTRATIVE PROVISIONS OF THE CODE.
THIS ITEM WAS REFERRED WITHOUT RECOMMENDATION FROM THE BUDGET
AND FINANCE COMMITTEE. THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
SO I WOULD LIKE TO SPEAK ON THIS BUT I'M NOT GOING TO DO IT
FROM THE DAIS AND SO I WOULD LIKE TO INVITE SUPERVISOR
MELGAR TO COME UP AND CHAIR THIS PART OF THE MEETING.
OKAY. SUPERVISOR CHIN THANK YOU CHAIR
MALCOLM I'M SORRY BUT ACTUALLY I GUESS DO YOU WANT TO SPEAK
FIRST? >> FIRST I'M SORRY HE HADN'T
PUT HIS NAME ON THE ROSTER YET SO WOULD YOU LIKE THIS IS YOUR
ITEM? YEAH.
GO AHEAD. >> SUPERVISOR PRESIDENT AND ALL
RIGHT, COLLEAGUES, THIS ITEM IS ONE ON WHICH I THINK REASONABLE
PEOPLE CAN DISAGREE BUT I STRONGLY BELIEVE AS I HAVE
BELIEVED FOR A NUMBER OF YEARS NOW EVER SINCE THIS TAX WAS
PASSED IN 2018 THAT IT IS NOT APPROPRIATE TO BE SUBJECTING
THE LEGAL CANNABIS INDUSTRY TO ADDITIONAL BURDENS AT THIS TIME
OUR CANNABIS MARKET REMAINS HIGHLY COMPETITIVE AND FRANKLY
THE COMPETITION IS BEING LOST BY OUR LEGAL OPERATORS.
THE ILLICIT SECTOR IS DOMINANT CONTROLS MORE THAN 50% OF THE
MARKET. THEY SELL THEIR PRODUCTS AT
SUBSTANTIALLY LOWER PRICES. THEY ARE NOT SUBJECT TO THE
SAME REGULATORY AND TAX OBLIGATIONS THAT LEGAL
OPERATORS ARE SUBJECT TO AND TO BE CLEAR THOSE ILLICIT SELLERS
DO NOT PAY TAXES. THEY DO NOT APPLY FOR BUSINESS
PERMITS. THEIR PRODUCT IS NOT SUBJECTED
TO THE RIGOROUS QUALITY CONTROL THAT LEGAL OPERATORS ARE
SUBJECT TO AND SO I HAVE BELIEVED SINCE THIS TAX PASSED
IN 2018 AND CONTINUE TO BELIEVE THAT IT IS NOT AND WILL NOT BE
APPROPRIATE TO BE SUBJECTING THIS INDUSTRY TO THE LEGAL
INDUSTRY TO MORE BURDENS UNTIL THE FACTORS THAT ARE UNFAIRLY
BURDENING THAT INDUSTRY ARE ALLEVIATED.
THERE IS NO INDICATION THAT THAT IS COMING ON THE HORIZON.
I HAVE AUTHORED THREE PRIOR DEFERRALS OF THIS TAX.
>> THE FIRST PASSED IN 2020 PASSED THE HOUSE TO PUSH THE
COLLECTION DATE BACK TO DECEMBER 2021.
>> THE SECOND PUSHED IT BACK TO DECEMBER 2022 AND IN LATE 2022
WE PUSHED IT BACK THROUGH DECEMBER OF OF THIS YEAR AT THE
BUDGET COMMITTEE THIS YEAR I DID INDICATE THAT I WAS
CONCERNED THAT OUR BUDGET PROJECTIONS WERE SHOWING THIS
AS A REVENUE SOURCE IN THE SECOND YEAR OF OUR CURRENT
BUDGET. I THOUGHT THAT WAS A MISTAKE
AND I SAID THAT I WOULD TRY TO ADDRESS IT GOING FORWARD OVER
THE COURSE OF THIS YEAR IN CONVERSATIONS WITH
COLLEAGUES IT HAS BEEN POINTED OUT TO ME AND I AGREE THAT
IN GENERAL WHEN WE HAVE RECEIVED FROM THE VOTERS
AUTHORITY TO TAX WE SHOULD BE LOATH TO GIVE IT AWAY FOR EVER
. AND SO RATHER THAN DOING AN
ELIMINATION OF THIS TAX WE HAVE ASKED THE BUDGET AND FINANCE
COMMITTEE AND I WANT TO THANK THE MEMBERS OF THE BUDGET
FINANCE COMMITTEE FOR TURNING THAT ELIMINATION INTO A TEN
YEAR DEFERRAL. I THINK THAT IS A DECENT PERIOD
MAYBE THE WORLD WILL HAVE CHANGED IN TEN YEARS.
MAYBE THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT WILL HAVE COME TO THEIR SENSES
AND AND BE REGULATING CANNABIS IN A REASONABLE WAY AND MAYBE
OUR STATE THE STATE TAX BURDEN WILL HAVE BEEN REDUCED
AND MAYBE AT THAT POINT IT WILL BE APPROPRIATE FOR SAN
FRANCISCO TO BEGIN COLLECTING THIS TAX.
BUT I CANNOT IMAGINE AND I HOPE THAT'S WHAT HAPPENS BUT I DON'T
SEE THAT HAPPENING IN THE NEAR FUTURE AND SO I THINK IT MAKES
SENSE TO FOR OUR OWN PLANNING PURPOSES AND FOR THE LEGAL
INDUSTRY THAT IS TRYING TO PLAN TO PUSH THIS TAX FAR OUT.
I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISORS DORSEY, SADR AND MAHMOOD FOR
THEIR CO-SPONSORSHIP OF THE ORDINANCE AND I WANT TO THANK
MY LEGISLATIVE AIDE SOPHIE MARIE FOR HER WORK AS WELL
AND I WOULD RESPECTFULLY ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT FOR THE
ORDINANCE TODAY. THAT'S IT.
OKAY. SUPERVISOR CHIN CHAIR MARKER.
THANK YOU. >> I HAVE VOTED AGAINST A
SUSPENSION OF THIS TAX PREVIOUSLY WHEN IT WAS PROPOSED
TO BE SUSPENDED FOR THREE FISCAL YEARS.
>> COLLEAGUES, WE CONTINUE TO FACE CLOSE TO A $1 BILLION
BUDGET DEFICIT. WE ARE GOING TO LEARN MORE
IN THE COMING WEEKS. >> AND FEDERAL CUTS ARE
EXPECTED TO GREATLY EXACERBATE OUR DEFICIT.
AS YOUR BUDGET COMMITTEE CHAIR, I'VE ALWAYS BEEN COMMITTED TO
FULFILLING OUR SHARED BUDGET PRIORITIES FROM PROVIDING
SUPPORT TO OUR MOST VULNERABLE. WHEN THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT CUT
FOOD NUTRITION PROGRAMS LIKE SNAP TO ADDITIONAL FUNDING FOR
IMMIGRATION LEGAL AID SETTING ASIDE A RESERVE TO SAFEGUARD
AGAINST HEALTH CARE CUTS AND PRIORITIZING FUNDING FOR
CRITICAL PROGRAMS LIKE FREE MUNI FOR YOUTH FEE WAIVERS FOR
SMALL BUSINESSES, CRITICAL SERVICES SUPPORTING THE LGBTQ
COMMUNITY, PUBLIC SAFETY INITIATIVES AND MUCH MORE ALL
OF ALL OF WHICH WE ACCOMPLISHED TOGETHER WHILE WE ALSO TACKLE
THREATS TO CITY WORKER LAYOFFS ,FEDERAL CUTS AND STATE BUDGET
DEFICIT THIS COMING YEAR WILL BE EVEN MORE DIFFICULT NOT
BECAUSE OF WHAT WE DO OR DON'T DO ON A LOCAL LEVEL BUT ALSO
BECAUSE OF THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT'S CONTINUING
THREATENS OUR LOCAL AND STATE GOVERNMENTS.
WE CANNOT THOUGH JUST TO CUT OUR WAY OUT TO BACK TO A
BALANCED BUDGET WE MUST ALSO MAINTAIN AND INCREASE OUR TAX
REVENUES TO WAIVE ANY TAX REVENUE FOR TEN YEARS FOR A
PROJECTED $80 MILLION IN TAX REVENUE WITHOUT OTHER CRITICAL
BUDGET AND FINANCIAL ANALYSIS THAT WE WOULD TYPICALLY HAVE
DURING THE BUDGET PROCESS. IT'S SIMPLY IRRESPONSIBLE.
>> I THINK WE CAN DO THIS. WE CAN DO THIS AND HAVE THIS
CONVERSATION DURING THE BUDGET PROCESS.
BUT IN THE MIDDLE IN THE MIDDLE OF A FISCAL YEAR I DON'T
UNDERSTAND WHY WE MUST DO THIS RIGHT NOW.
THERE'S NOT A GOOD REASON. SO THIS IS WHY I WILL BE VOTING
AGAINST THIS TEN YEAR SUSPENSION OF A CANNABIS
BUSINESS TAX. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD THANK YOU
SENATOR MCGAURAN. THANK YOU.
PRESENT GENTLEMEN FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP ON THIS ITEM.
I SUPPORT CONTINUING THE SUSPENSION OF THE CANNABIS TAX
AND I WILL ADMIT AS SOMEONE WHO HAS NEVER USED CANNABIS
IN THEIR LIFE I NEVER THOUGHT I WOULD BE VOCIFEROUSLY DEFENDING
THIS LEGISLATION. AND THE REASON IS IS THAT IF WE
DON'T VOTE TO SUSPEND THIS TAX TODAY, LEGAL TAXPAYING CANNABIS
RETAILERS WILL FACE YET ANOTHER SETBACK.
>> CANNABIS BUSINESSES ARE AMONG THE TOUGHEST TO RUN
IN SAN FRANCISCO AND THESE BUSINESSES ARE SMALL BUSINESSES
AND AS NASCENT BUSINESSES THEY FACE A CHALLENGING PLANNING
AND LEASING LANDSCAPE THAT ARE ALREADY TAXED AT NEARLY 30% AT
THE STATE LEVEL AND BY OUR CITY'S GENERAL GROSS RECEIPTS
TAX. >> THESE ADDITIONAL COSTS
AND DIFFICULTIES THAT ARE IMPOSED AS A RESULT OF THE DRUG
ILLEGALITY AT THE FEDERAL LEVEL ONLY COMPOUNDS THIS ISSUE.
>> AND SO SUSPENDING THIS TAX WILL GIVE THE INDUSTRY MORE
BREATHING ROOM TO MAKE UP GROUND AGAINST ILLEGAL UNTAXED
BLACK MARKETS THAT ARE STILL THRIVING ON OUR STREETS BECAUSE
OF THIS DOUBLE TAXATION AT THE HIGH LEVEL FROM STATE AND LOCAL
LEVELS. IT CAUSES THESE BUSINESSES TO
PASS ON THAT COST TO THE CONSUMER RAISING THE PRICES
AND IN TURN ALLOWING FOR AN ILLEGAL BLACK MARKET TO
UNDERCUT AND FESTER ON OUR STREETS.
>> AND WHILE I UNDERSTAND THIS, THE ISSUE RAISED BY MY
COLLEAGUES ABOUT A LOSS IN POTENTIAL TAX REVENUE, WHAT
WE'RE FAILING TO ACCOUNT FOR SIMULTANEOUSLY ARE NEGATIVE
EXTERNALITIES THAT RESULT AS A RESULT OF THIS TAX.
>> I CHALLENGE ANYONE TO WALK THROUGH MY DISTRICT IN THE
TENDERLOIN THAT IS HEAVILY AFFECTED BY THIS AND THIS
ISSUE. >> IF YOU GO TO MARKET IN JONES
AT THE CORNER THERE THERE HAS BEEN A THRIVING ILLEGAL BLACK
MARKET FOR CANNABIS. >> AND WHAT YOU SEE HAPPENING
AROUND THAT NEIGHBORHOOD IS THE PROPER HOTEL IS LOSING REVENUE.
>> THE HIBERNIA BANK WHERE THEIR EVENT VENUE IS THERE IS
LOSING REVENUE. >> THE MOSQUE THAT I PRAY AT
RIGHT THERE IS FACING SIGNIFICANT CHALLENGES BECAUSE
RIGHT IN THE MIDDLE OF IT IS AN ILLEGAL CANNABIS MARKET THAT IS
SALES TAX REVENUE THAT ALSO SHOULD BE ASSESSED
AND UNDERSTOOD AS POTENTIALLY BEING LOST IF WE CONTINUE TO
DISSUADE THESE BUSINESSES FROM OPERATING LEGALLY FROM FROM A
CANNABIS PERSPECTIVE WE DRIVE OUT MORE BUYERS AND SELLERS
INTO THE BLACK MARKET SIMULTANEOUSLY.
>> THIS IS A PUBLIC SAFETY CONCERN.
>> EVERY DAY I WALK TO AND FROM CITY HALL PAST THAT
INTERSECTION AT MARKET IN JONES AND ALSO WHERE 3500 CHILDREN
ARE WALKING TO AND FROM SCHOOL AS WELL.
>> ON THAT CORNER OF MARKET AT JONES JUST THIS YEAR THERE HAS
BEEN A STABBING THAT PUT SOMEONE IN THE HOSPITAL.
THERE WAS A COUPLE THAT CAME OUT OF THE MOSQUE THAT I PRAY
THAT WAS ASSAULTED AND THE AND RIGHT AFTER THAT INCIDENT
THESE ARE ALL PUBLIC SAFETY IMPLICATIONS OF A BLACK MARKET
THAT IS PERSISTING ON OUR STREETS.
>> AND SO WHEN WE INCREASE THE PRICE OF LEGAL CANNABIS, WE
MAKE THINGS HARDER FOR BUSINESSES BIG AND SMALL AND WE
CREATE CONDITIONS ON OUR STREETS THAT ARE ALLOWING
PUBLIC SAFETY CHALLENGES TO EMERGE.
IT ALSO CREATES RETAIL VACANCIES ON MARKET STREET THAT
IF YOU WALK DOWN YOU WILL SEE ON THAT SAME CORNER EFFECTIVELY
IS ENTIRELY VACANT. >> AND WE WILL CAUSE THOSE
VACANCIES TO PERSIST LONGER AND BUSINESSES WILL SEE GREATLY
REDUCED FOOT TRAFFIC. IF WE AS A BOARD MAKE THE
CHOICE FOR MORE AND MORE CUSTOMERS TO GO TO THE STREETS
ULTIMATELY IT IS THE MAYOR WHO SENDS A BUDGET EVERY YEAR FOR
US TO RESPOND TO AND IS NOT IS HAPPENING RIGHT NOW.
THAT IS WHY I THINK THE TIMING OF THIS LEGISLATION IS
IMPORTANT BECAUSE WE ARE SIGNALING AS A BOARD WHAT ARE
OUR VALUES AS A BOARD AND HOW WE WANT THE MAYOR TO PRIORITIZE
POLICY. AND SO THE QUESTION OF WHERE
OUR REVENUE COMES FROM MUST BE ANSWERED BY MAYOR LURIE FIRST.
I'M MORE THAN COMFORTABLE WITH THE POLICY CHOICE THAT THIS
REVENUE DOES NOT COME FROM PUNISHING SMALL BUSINESSES TO
THE BENEFIT OF STREET DEALERS THAT MAKE OUR NEIGHBORHOODS
LESS DANGEROUS AND MORE LIVABLE.
OUR BUDGET IS, AS I SAID, A REFLECTION OF OUR VALUES
AND IMPOSING THIS TAX DOES NOT REFLECT OUR VALUES.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU SO
MUCH, CHAIR MELGAR. THERE WAS A TIME PERIOD WHERE I
DEFINITELY AGREE WITH OUR PRESIDENT AND WAS ACTUALLY A
MAJOR SUPPORTER OF SUSPENDING THIS TAX FOR ACTUALLY A FEW
YEARS. >> BUT IF WE LOOK AT THE STATE
OF OUR BUDGET IN SAN FRANCISCO, THERE'S NO WAY WE CAN
RESPONSIBLY SUSPEND THIS TAX IN MY OPINION.
>> I DO HAVE A COUPLE OF QUESTIONS FOR OUR COMPTROLLER
THROUGH THE CHAIR. THE FIRST ONE IS WHAT IS THE
PROJECTED BUDGET DEFICIT FOR THE UPCOMING FISCAL YEAR?
SUPERVISORS GREG WAGNER COMPTROLLER THROUGH THE CHAIR
TO SUPERVISOR WALTON MY OFFICE, THE MAYOR'S BUDGET OFFICE
AND THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYST
ARE CURRENTLY WORKING RIGHT NOW ON AN UPDATE TO THE DEFICIT
WHICH WILL BE OUT IN THE NEAR FUTURE.
SO I DON'T HAVE AN UPDATED NUMBER BUT I CAN TELL YOU AS A
KIND OF GENERAL DESCRIPTION OF OUR FINANCIAL POSITION IN OUR
MOST RECENT FIVE YEAR PROJECTION ISSUED IN MARCH
2025, THE FORECAST WAS THAT AN IMBALANCE BETWEEN REVENUES
AND EXPENDITURES SHOWED GROWTH IN THE DEFICIT IN EXCESS OF $1
BILLION BY THE END OF THE FIVE YEAR FINANCIAL FORECAST.
>> THANK YOU. AND DO WE KNOW THE PROJECTED
REVENUE IF WE DIDN'T SUSPEND THIS TAX THE REVENUE VARIES A
BIT BY YEAR TO YEAR BASED ON THE SCHEDULE FOR THE
ADMINISTRATION OF THE TAX BUT $6.2 MILLION PER YEAR IS THE
AVERAGE PROJECTED TAX REVENUE ONCE THE TAX IS IMPLEMENTED.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH COMPTROLLER.
>> SO AS WE CAN SEE WE HAVE FORECASTS OF AT LEAST A BILLION
DOLLAR BUDGET DEFICIT GOING INTO THE NEXT YEAR AND TO TURN
AROUND SUSPEND FORMS OF REVENUE.
I JUST TRULY, COMPLETELY FEEL THAT'S PRETTY IRRESPONSIBLE ON
OUR PART. THE PANDEMIC AND THE DEFICIT
MOST CERTAINLY HAVE BEEN HARD ON A LOT OF OUR INDUSTRIES HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO. I THINK WE'VE DONE A LOT TO
ADDRESS THAT AND OF COURSE WE'LL HAVE TO CONTINUE TO DO
THAT. BUT I ALSO KNOW THAT WE'RE
CHALLENGED WITH MAKING SURE THAT WE MAINTAIN A LEVEL OF
SERVICES FOR ALL OF OUR RESIDENTS.
I THINK THAT ALL STREAMS OF REVENUE WE NEED TO MAKE SURE WE
ARE PUSHING FOR THAT SUPPORT PARTICULARLY DURING THIS BUDGET
TIME WE'VE WAIVED THIS TAX FOR YEARS AND I JUST DON'T SEE HOW
WE CAN CONTINUE TO DO THAT PARTICULARLY CARVING THIS OUT
FOR THIS PARTICULAR INDUSTRY. LOT OF INDUSTRIES COULD REQUEST
SOME RELIEF IF WE REALLY LOOKED AND DID AN ANALYSIS OF
INDUSTRIES THAT ARE SUFFERING DURING THIS TIME PERIOD.
AND I THINK ONE OF THE THINGS THAT I WANT US ALL TO ALSO
UNDERSTAND IS THAT THIS TAX WILL NOT STOP THE BLACK MARKET.
SO IF IF THAT IS OUR REASONING, IT JUST DOESN'T GEL WHAT WAS
HAPPENING HERE IN THE STATE OF THIS NATION.
THE REALITY OF IT IS ONLY FEDERAL LEGALIZATION WILL DO
THAT AND PUT A DENT IN WHAT'S HAPPENING WITHIN THE BLACK
MARKET. BUT THIS TAX SUSPENSION WILL
NOT STOP THE BLACK MARKET. AND I KNOW THAT THIS IS AN
ATTEMPT TO PROTECT AN INDUSTRY THAT HAS BEEN TREATED UNFAIRLY
. BUT MOST CERTAINLY WE HAVE A
DEFICIT THAT IS HISTORICALLY THE LARGEST DEFICIT WE'VE SEEN
IN THIS CITY AND TO GIVE UP TAX REVENUE I JUST DON'T THINK IT
WILL BE RESPONSIVE ALL OF US TO DO THAT.
THANK YOU CHAIR MEMBER THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDOLIN.
>> JUST A NOTE ON TIMING AND WHY WE WOULD DO IT NOW
RATHER THAN THROUGH THE NORMAL BUDGET PROCESS NEXT YEAR THIS
TAX IS SET TO BE START BEING COLLECTED IN 2026 SO IF WE ARE
GOING TO HAVE OUR TREASURY TAX COLLECTOR NOT COLLECT THAT TAX,
WE NEED TO ACT NOW TO TO TO NOT HAVE THIS TAX START.
IT IS A TAX THAT HAS NOT BEEN COLLECTED.
>> SO IT IS IT WOULD BE A NEW BURDEN ON THESE BUSINESSES
AND IF WE WERE TO TRY TO ADDRESS IT THROUGH THE BUDGET
PROCESS THIS IS SORT OF ECHOING SUPERVISOR MAHMOUD'S POINT.
THIS IS PROBABLY AN AMOUNT THAT IS MORE THAN THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS CAN COME UP WITH THROUGH OUR ADD BACK PROCESS.
BUT IS A TINY, TINY TINY PIECE OF A $15 BILLION BUDGET.
>> SO SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU CHAIR MOGAHED I JUST WANT
TO SAY THAT 2026 IS EXACTLY THE PERFECT TIMING FOR THIS TAX TO
BE COLLECTED AND TO COME INTO EFFECT AGAIN.
WE'VE HEARD THE PREDICTED DEFICIT FROM FROM THE
COMPTROLLER AND I HOPE THAT WHEN WE GO THROUGH THIS BUDGET
PROCESS AND WE START GOING BACK AND FORTH OVER WHAT WE NEED TO
PRIORITIZE, I HOPE TO HEAR AGAIN THAT $6.5 MILLION IS A
SMALL PART OF THIS BUDGET WHEN THERE ARE OTHER PRIORITIES THAT
WE'RE GOING TO BE FIGHTING FOR THAT IS BUDGET PROCESS BECAUSE
I HAVE A FEELING THAT FOLKS WILL BE SAYING THAT $6.5
MILLION IS NOT A SMALL AMOUNT OF MONEY.
WHEN WE TALK ABOUT CERTAIN PRIORITIES WHEN WE GO THROUGH
THE BUDGET PROCESS. >> THANK YOU CHAIR MEMBER THANK
YOU. OKAY.
I THINK THAT'S ALL I HAVE ON THE ROSTER.
MADAM CLERK ON ITEM 29. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISE FOR MENDELSOHN HI MENDELSOHN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
I MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I THERE ARE AS EIGHT EYES
AND TWO NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS WALTON AND CHAN VOTING NO
AND SORRY THE ORDINANCE THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST
READING. >> ALL RIGHT MADAM CLERK LET'S
GO TO OUR 230 SPECIAL ORDER IT IS NOW 230 AND TIME FOR THE
RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATIONS FOR MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE
CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> AND WE WILL START TODAY WITH DISTRICT 11 SUPERVISOR CHEN.
>> THANK YOU FOR PRESIDENT. >> MAY I HAVE OSCAR GRANTED TO
GO WALK TO THE PODIUM? >> WE ALL LOVE YOU, OSCAR.
COLLEAGUES, MANY YEARS AGO A JANITOR AT THE SAN FRANCISCO
CHRONICLE ON MISSION STREET FELL IN LOVE WITH A SEAMSTRESS
AND THE OLD LEVI STRAUSS JEANS FACTORY ON VALENCIA STREET
LEAVING THEIR STORY OF THE AMERICAN DREAM AS HOW WORKING
FIRST GENERATION IMMIGRANTS FROM EL SALVADOR THEY BOUGHT
YOUNG OSCAR MARTIN GRANDI INTO THIS WORLD.
YEAH, THIS GUY CAME OUT ON THE STREETS OF THE EXCELSIOR
DISTRICT. >> HE ATTENDED CORPUS CHRISTI
ELEMENTARY SCHOOL AND SECRET HEART CASHEW JEWEL REPERTORY
HIGH SCHOOL. >> YEAH.
OSCAR LATER ATTENDED SAN FRANCISCO STATE UNIVERSITY
WHERE HE FELL IN LOVE WITH CYNTHIA MEZA, A PUBLIC SCHOOL
EDUCATOR. AND TOGETHER THEY HAVE FOUR
CHILDREN SO SEE OMAR SEE OMAR NYLA, SOPHIA AND AND MOLLY WHO
THEY RAISED IN THE SAME CHILDHOOD HOME WHERE OSCAR GREW
UP AS A YOUNG MAN OSCAR BEGAN WORKING IN COMMUNITY AT THE
REAL ALTERNATIVES PROGRAM WHERE HE WHERE HE WAS MENTOR BY THE
OGS AND HIMSELF BECAME A MENTOR TO YOUNG PEOPLE SURVIVING ON
THE STREETS OF THE MISSIONS. >> FOR THOSE WHO DON'T KNOW
OSCAR, HE HAS A SHINING SPIRIT ,A COMMANDING PRESENCE
AND INFECTIOUS SENSE OF HUMOR AND DEEPLY ROOTED IN SENSE OF
COMMUNITY. >> LET ME WALK YOU THROUGH SOME
OF HIS MANY LASTING LEGACIES. >> OSCAR'S FAMOUSLY SPENT MUCH
OF HIS ADULT CAREER AS A COMMUNITY ORGANIZER WITH PEOPLE
ORGANIZING TO DEMAND ENVIRONMENTAL AND ECONOMIC
RIGHTS IN SAN FRANCISCO SUBMISSIONS DISTRICT.
>> AS A CO-FOUNDER OF THE MISSION ANTI DISPLACEMENT
COALITIONS, OSCAR HELPED TO CRAFT A PEOPLE'S PLAN FOR JOBS,
HOUSING AND COMMUNITY. >> THE EIGHT YEARS THE EIGHT
YEAR COMMUNITY ORGANIZING EFFORT HELPED TO CREATE LAND
USE POLICIES TO SECURE AFFORDABLE HOUSING GREEN SPACE
LOCALLY OWNED IT COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS AND JOB CREATIONS FOR
THE MISSION DISTRICT. >> ANTONIO DIAZ, ORGANIZATIONAL
DIRECTOR OF PODER HE SAID OF OSCAR I REMEMBER HOW HE
POWERFUL HE SPOKE TRUTH TO POWER.
>> WHEN MAC HAD THEN PLANNING COMMISSIONER PRESIDENT GERALD
GREEN AND TWO COMMISSIONERS ATTEND A COMMUNITY MEETING
ACCOUNTABILITY SECTION AT THE HORACE MANN MIDDLE SCHOOL BACK
IN 2000, OSCAR HAS BEEN OUR SOLUTION NERI ACTING OUT OF
DEEP LOVE FOR HIS FAMILY, COMMUNITY AND FOR A VIBRANT SAN
FRANCISCO. >> WHEN MANY LOW INCOME
AND WORKING CLASS COMMUNITY WERE FIRST HIT AND THE WORST
DURING THE GREAT ECONOMIC RECEPTION OSCAR ORGANIZED IT
WITH MONOLINGUAL IMMIGRANT NEIGHBORHOOD LEADERS TO
FORMALIZE MUTUAL AID STRATEGIES SUCH AS A TIME BANK AND WORKER
COOPERATIVE RESTAURANT MIHAIL LUNA IN THE MISSION DISTRICT.
>> OSCAR CONTRIBUTED HIS PASSION FOR BICYCLES AS A
CO-FOUNDER OF B C DA PORTABLE PREBLE THIS BY UP LET MOBILITY
FREEDOM EFFORT IT'S A COMMUNITY COOPERATIVE PROGRAM COOPERATIVE
PROGRAM TO PUT BICYCLES INTO THE HANDS OF EVERYDAY PEOPLE
TEACHING SAFETY AND WRITING SKILLS AND BUILDING COMMUNITY
THROUGH CULTURALLY BASED BI PRACTICES IN HIS IN THE FIRST
MONTH OF PANDEMIC, OSCAR GRANDI JOINED WITH DISTRICT 11
NEIGHBORS TO ESTABLISH THE FIRST FREE TESTING SITE AT OUR
AMAZON CLUBHOUSE POW YAY! >> POWERED BY VOLUNTEERS THEIR
SITE WAS ABLE TO PROCESS UP TO 800 TESTS PER DAY BEFORE
APPOINTMENTS WERE EVEN OFFER BY COPYRIGHT INSURANCE COMPANIES.
>> OSCAR WAS ALSO PART OF THE TEAM THAT CREATED ME MY MI
MERCADO PROGRAM THAT PROVIDED 400 FAMILIES WITH A DEBIT CARD
FOR USE AT A EXCELSIOR GROCERY STORES AND RELOADED THEM WITH
880,000 FOR FOOD DURING SHELTER IN PLACE FROM THE FRONTLINES OF
PUBLIC HEALTH CRISIS, HE WAS ABLE TO ADVOCATE FOR THE MOST
VULNERABLE OF OUR NEIGHBORS AND PERSONALLY ENSURE THOSE
SERVICES WERE DELIVERED. >> OSCAR SERVES IN THE CAMPUS
ADDRESS COUNCIL AT CASA DE PAULA.
>> HE HAS BEEN A PART OF THE GROWING THE SPACE FROM
ABANDONED FLOWER SHOP INTO A VIBE AND HOPPED FOR RESOURCES,
PUBLIC HEALTH COMMUNITY DRIVEN ACTIONS, JOB DEVELOPMENT,
NEIGHBORHOOD GIVEBACKS AND A BIKE SHOP.
FOR THE PAST FIVE YEARS HE HAS LED A TEAM TO HOST A HOLIDAY
BIKE GIVEAWAY AND HOST AN ANNUAL BIKE RIGHT FOR FATHER'S
DAY. OSCAR CARRIES THE SPIRITS OF
SOLIDARY ITY AND ORGANIZING TO ENSURE OUR SAN FRANCISCO
WORKING CLASS FAMILIES ARE THE FOREFRONT OF RECEIVING THE
RESOURCES THEY NEED TO THRIVE HAVE THE SKILLS TO BE DECISION
MAKER IN THEIR COMMUNITIES. WE'RE LAUGHING MAKING EVERYBODY
FEEL GOOD AND JOY AND CELEBRATING OUR VERY VERY
MUCH DIVERSE CULTURALLY ROOTED AND TRADITIONS TODAY AS OUR
COMMUNITIES ARE DEEPLY, DEEPLY GRATEFUL TO OSCAR FOR YOUR
YEARS OF SERVICE. >> THANK YOU OSCAR
BUT WAIT BECAUSE SUPERVISOR MELGAR WANTS TO TALK SO THANK
YOU SUPERVISOR CHAD SO MUCH FOR THIS WONDERFUL HONOR TO MY
COMPANERO HERE AND FELLOW SELFIE BIKE ENTHUSIAST OSCAR
FIRST I JUST WANT TO SAY THAT I'M SO HAPPY TO SEE THE RESULTS
IN THE HOUSE, SO GLAD THAT THE WHOLE COMMUNITY CAME OUT TO
SUPPORT OSCAR IN CYNTHIA TOO WHO IS MY DANCE SISTER.
I DON'T HAVE TO GO THROUGH ALL OF THE WONDERFUL
ACCOMPLISHMENTS OF OSCAR AS AN ORGANIZER AND ALTHOUGH THE
WONDERFUL WORK THAT YOU'VE DONE BECAUSE SUPERVISOR CHAN ALREADY
DID A VERY THOROUGH COMPILATION BUT I JUST HAVE TO ADD THE
HUMAN ASPECT OF THIS WONDERFUL MAN FROM BEING A WONDERFUL SON
AND COMMUNITY MEMBER AND A HUSBAND YOU AND CYNTHIA HAVE
PRODUCED FOR OUR STAFF AND BEING HUMAN BEINGS WHO ARE
SO CONNECTED TO THE COMMUNITY, SO SMART, SO CREATIVE
AND ARTISTIC AND ARE GIVING BACK TO THIS WORLD BECAUSE YOU
ARE WONDERFUL HUMAN BEINGS AND IN ADDITION TO ALL OF THE
WONDERFUL THINGS THAT YOU'VE DONE TO THE COMMUNITY, TO THOSE
OF US THAT KNOW YOU OSCAR GOING BACK FOUR DECADES THAT I'VE
KNOWN YOU AND YOU KNOW, DEBATED POLICY ISSUES AND ALSO GIVEN
CAREER ADVICE AND EVERYTHING IN BETWEEN, I JUST HAVE SO MUCH
PROFOUND RESPECT FOR YOU AND I KNOW NOT JUST THE WORK THAT
YOU'VE DONE BUT WHO YOU ARE AS A HUMAN AND WHAT YOU HAVE DONE
IN THIS WORLD. SO MUCH LOVE, SO MUCH COMMUNITY
AND THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOU KNOW, BEING PART OF OUR
COMMUNITY. THANK YOU.
>> AND NOW THE FLOOR IS YOURS MOLD AND I AM JUST FILLED WITH
A LOT OF EMOTIONS RIGHT NOW JUST LISTENING TO SUPERVISOR
TEN SUPERVISOR MARION GOD WE GO WAY BACK GO WAY BACK.
>> SUPERVISOR CHANNER THE CPA, THE CHINESE PROGRESS
ASSOCIATION DAYS AND THE UNION DAYS AND AND I'M JUST SO
BLESSED AND HUMBLED TO BE SURROUNDED BY MY MY FAMILIA MY
LOVED ONES, MY COMRADES, MY MY SISTER AND MY BRETHREN.
I MEAN THIS IS I'M NOT WITHOUT COMMUNITY YOU KNOW ALL THOSE
THOSE ACCOLADES, THOSE ACHIEVEMENTS, THOSE IT'S JUST
NOT A ALONE IT'S IT'S ALL OF US ALL OF US TOGETHER HAVE
CO-CREATED THIS AND AND AND I'M A LITTLE AND IT'S A LITTLE
BITTERSWEET FOR ME YOU KNOW AND FOR MANY OF US HERE THAT
LEARNING OF THE PASSING OF A DEAR BROTHER RICARDO PENA,
RICARDO PENA PRESENT DAY RICARDO PENA PRESENT DAY DEAR
BROTHER FROM MY THAT'S OUR SPIRITUAL COMMUNITY ARE 24TH
STREET COMMUNITY THAT PASSED YESTERDAY SO IT IS BITTERSWEET
AND IT MAKES ME THINK ABOUT THE ANCESTORS WHO FOLLOWED AND WHO
SHOWED US THE PATH, WHO SHOWED ME THE PATH, WHOSE SHOULDERS I
STAND ON AND YOU KNOW NAMELY MY MOTHER AND MY FATHER OSCAR NAM
. >> AND YOU KNOW, I THINK ABOUT
THE BROTHER MIGUEL MARTINEZ. >> IT'S HARD TO THINK ABOUT
ERIC CASADA AND I THINK ABOUT SOME OF THOSE PHENOMENAL
ORGANIZERS LIKE MARIE HARRISON, SHARON HEWITT I THINK ABOUT
JESSE COLLINS, SOME OF THE OGS WE TALKED ABOUT THE ABOUT BILL
SORROW AND I JUST WAS RECENTLY THINKING ABOUT OUR RTA WHO
RECENTLY PASSED MEANT TO SAY THIS GARRIDO WHO WAS A FIRST
GENERATION A SALVADORIAN IMMIGRANTS THAT CAME TO THIS
COUNTRY AND REALLY PAVED THE WAY FOR OUR FAMILY TO COME OVER
AND TO PLANT ROOTS HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO AND TO BUILD A LIFE.
AND AS MY KIDS ARE THAT SECOND GENERATION OF SAN FRANCISCANS
YOU KNOW WITH ROOTS IN THEIR SALVADOR I YOU KNOW THINK ABOUT
AND I AND I THINK PROFOUNDLY MY LOVED ONES AND MY COMRADES FROM
MY WIFE CYNTHIA MEZA WHO'S A 25 YEAR S.F. UCD SCHOOLTEACHER
BESIDES BEING A PHENOMENAL WIFE ,COMPANERO AND BEST FRIEND, AN
AMAZING TEACHER EDUCATOR I SHARED WITH YOU HOW TO AND I
THINK ABOUT MY KIDS AND I HAVE NYLA SO BEYOND I HAVE HALF
SAMARRA HERE MALI IS AT MISSION HIGH GO BEARS.
SHE GOT FINALS COMING UP NEXT WEEK.
SO AND THEN YOU KNOW AND ALL THESE FOLKS THAT ARE
SURROUNDING HERE AND AND I THINK WHAT I'VE LEARNED OVER
THE YEARS IS REALLY WHAT HAS MADE ME AND WHAT GUIDES ME
AND WHAT IS MY MORAL COMPASS POINT IS REALLY THE MOVEMENT'S
SPIRITUAL CULTURAL POLITICAL MOVEMENTS THE ASSEMBLY OF LOVED
ONES THAT ARE HERE TODAY AND THOSE THAT COULDN'T MAKE IT
THERE HAVE BEEN BLESSED TO KNOW AND GROW FROM.
THESE ARE FOLKS FROM MY ENVIRONMENTAL JUSTICE COMMUNITY
WHERE I CUT MY TEETH AS A YOUNG ORGANIZER THERE, YOU KNOW, OF
OF THE SACREDNESS OF LAND AND BEING IN HARMONY WITH WITH
MOTHER EARTH AND AND ORGANIZING ALONGSIDE WORKING PEOPLE
AND PEOPLE ARE MOST IMPACTED BY THE INJUSTICES THAT THAT THAT
WE FACE TODAY. BUT THERE IS MY CULTURAL
SPIRITUAL POLITICAL HOME THAT'S WHERE I CUT MY TEETH AND THE
MAZING STAFF THAT'S HERE CONTINUING TO DO THAT WORK
BUILDING OFF OF THAT LEGACY OF FIGHTING FOR LAND AND FIGHTING
FOR THE PEOPLE OF THE MISSION EXCELSIOR AND CITY I THINK RUN
MY BIKE LIBERATION SPACES WHERE I LEARNED CORPORATISM,
COLLECTIVISM, MUTUAL AID AND RECIPROCITY.
>> THE ONLY CHANGE THAT SET US FREE ARE THOSE BIKE CHAINS.
I GET THAT FROM OUR ANARCHIST BROTHERS AND SISTERS, YOU KNOW
AND HOUSING JUSTICE MENTIONED MRD ANTI DISPLACEMENT COALITION
YOU KNOW THAT ANTI DISPLACEMENT WORK THAT WE ALL CO-CREATED YOU
KNOW EARLY 2000S YOU KNOW WHERE A LOT OF US LEARNED AND GREW
HAVE GROWN FROM TO REALLY ELEVATE THE HOUSING JUSTICE
WORK THAT IS FRONT AND CENTER STILL TO THIS DAY WE HAVE NOT
SOLVED THAT CRISIS AND AND AND I THINK ABOUT THE
AFFORDABLE HOUSING WORK AND THE ADVOCACY IN THE ORGANIZING WORK
WHEN WE SEE THE FRUITS OF THAT LABOR UP AND DOWN 16TH STREET
WITH ALL THEM BEAUTIFUL AFFORDABLE HOUSING BUILDINGS
THAT LINE THERE AND ALL THIS INFLUX OF NEW FAMILIES,
AFRICAN-AMERICAN FAMILIES, IMMIGRANT FAMILIES, FOLKS THAT
ARE RAISED IN THIS CITY, FOLKS THAT ARE REFUGEES AND ARE
FINDING RESPITE FROM THE HORRIBLE PLACES THEY'VE HAD TO
ESCAPE AND DANCE LATELY MY SPIRITUAL HOME AND THIS IS MY
SPIRITUAL HOME IT IS WHERE I YOU KNOW, WHERE WE PRACTICE OUR
MICHIKA CEREMONIAL DANCE TRADITIONS.
IT'S WHERE I HAVE REALLY LEARNED TO REGROUND MYSELF
IN SPIRITUALITY AS I MATURE AND AS I BECOME AN OLDER
AND ROOT OF BECOMING AN ELDER IT IS MORE CRITICAL
AND IMPORTANT AND DON'T SLEEP ON SPIRITUALITY.
>> YOUNG FOLKS AND AND AND ALSO WORKING WITH THE CITY FOR THE
PAST FEW YEARS ARE COMING HOME OF SOME SORTS BECAUSE I'M BACK
IN UNION SEIU 1021 AND AND AND AND MY PARENTS WERE UNION
MEMBERS JANITORS GARMENT WORKERS AND IT IS ONE OF THE
SOLID WAYS REALLY THAT IMMIGRANTS DURING THAT TIME
THAT CAME HERE WERE ABLE TO BUILD A LIFE BE ABLE TO PUT
DOWN ROOTS ACHIEVE YOU KNOW A LOWER MIDDLE CLASS LIFESTYLE
AND BE ABLE TO BUY SOME REAL ESTATE IN EXCELSIOR MISSION
BAYVIEW AND BEYOND AND THAT'S WHAT REALLY GUIDES ME
AND INSPIRES ME IN MY WORK ESPECIALLY AFTER ME AND MY
WIFE, MY FAMILY. WE JUST BOUGHT OUR CHILDHOOD
HOME AND I WANT THAT FOR ALL OF US.
>> SO THANK YOU SUPERVISORS. THANK YOU SUPER VISORS.
PLEASE CONTINUE DOING THE BUSINESS OF THE PEOPLE.
THANK YOU COMMUNITY. I LOVE YOU AND WE'LL SEE YOU
OUT ON THE STREETS
. SEEMS LIKE A ROTUNDA PHOTO
OPPORTUNITY SUPERVISOR CHAN I MEAN THEY'RE MAKING THEIR WAY.
I THINK THEY'RE THERE. THEY'LL GET OUT THERE.
YOU
ALL RIGHT? DISTRICT THREE SUPERVISOR
SAUTER. THANK YOU, PRESIDENT COLLEAGUES
TODAY I AM HAPPY TO WELCOME BILL ESCOBEDO, OWNER OF EL
PASTORE. PAPI MIGUEL, PLEASE COME UP
AND JOIN US. >> CHEF MIGUEL HAS BROUGHT HIS
MEXICO CITY STYLE EL PASTORE TO DISTRICT THREE WITH THE OPENING
OF EL PASTORE PAPI IN THE HEART OF UNION SQUARE.
THIS OPENING WAS RECENTLY MADE POSSIBLE THROUGH THE VACANT TO
VIBRANT PROGRAM AND IT PAIRED MIGUEL'S TALENT FOR COOKING
WITH HIS TALENT FOR MAKING PEOPLE FEEL RIGHT AT HOME.
I COULD HAVE BROUGHT HIM IN TODAY TO HONOR HIM FOR HIS
DELICIOUS FOOD AND HE WOULD HAVE DESERVE RECOGNITION FOR
THAT ALONE. AFTER ALL, HE IS THE GENIUS
BEHIND PABLO DE SALSA AND HE HAS TAKEN DOWN BOBBY FLAY
AND BEAT BOBBY FLAY BUT HE'S REALLY HERE BECAUSE OF THE
HEART BEHIND HIS FOOD AT HIS GRAND OPENING THIS SUMMER.
MIGUEL WAS QUICK TO MAKE THE DAY NOT ABOUT HIMSELF BUT MORE
SO ABOUT HIS STAFF. AND ON DAY ONE HE STARTED BY
DONATING HUNDREDS OF BURRITOS TO CITY EATS AND WE FANNED OUT
ACROSS THE TENDERLOIN TO DONATE THOSE MEALS TO NEIGHBORS.
WHEN WASHINGTON POLITICS THREATENED FOOD ACCESS FOR SAN
FRANCISCO FAMILIES, MIGUEL STEPPED UP.
HE OFFERED FREE BURRITOS EACH WEEK TO ANY FAMILY ON SNAP
AND THAT RESULTED IN MORE THAN 700 BURRITOS DISTRIBUTED
IN JUST A FEW WEEKS. AND RIGHT NOW IN THIS HOLIDAY
SEASON HE IS ORGANIZING HIS SEVENTH ANNUAL TOY DRIVE TO
COLLECT TOYS FOR KIDS OF FARMWORKERS BECAUSE HE KNOWS
ESPECIALLY THIS TIME OF YEAR NO KID SHOULD BE WITHOUT A REASON
FOR JOY IN THIS SEASON. HE IS A CHAMPION FOR OUR CITY.
HE IS A STAUNCH DEFENDER OF FARM WORKERS RIGHTS
AND IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES. >> AND ON TOP OF ALL THAT HE
HAPPENS TO BE A VERY, VERY TALENTED CHEF WHO IS DRAWING
HUGE CROWDS TO UNION SQUARE'S TASTIEST NEW RESTAURANT MIGUEL
. WE TYPICALLY OFFER FLOWERS TO
HONOREES IN THESE CHAMBERS BUT TODAY WE'RE GOING TO DISTRIBUTE
A TOY INSTEAD FOR YOUR HOLIDAY TOY DRIVE.
AND MIGUEL, THANK YOU FOR ALL YOU DO.
AND THE FLOOR IS YOURS TO SAY A FEW WORDS.
THANK YOU SO MUCH. THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THIS
RECOGNITION THAT IT MEANS A LOT .
AND IT'S FUNNY THAT MY MAN BEFORE ME IT I WISH YOU GUYS
WOULD HAVE DONE HIM AFTER ME. >> BUT I'VE WORKED WITH
AND WITH PAPA A LOT WHEN I HAD PAPA LOT WITH MY BROTHER WE
WORKED WITH BEASLEY'S AT PUEBLO.
WE BOTH WORKED WITH BOTH AS WE SUPPORTED A LOT OF PEOPLE THAT
SUPPORTED OUR COMMUNITY AS WELL AS OUR FARM WORKERS.
MY WHOLE THING IS JUST LIKE OSCAR SAID LIKE I'M NOTHING
WITHOUT MY COMMUNITY. I CAN BE A BUSINESS.
>> I CAN'T YOU KNOW, OPERATE WITHOUT GIVING BACK AND ALSO
BECAUSE OF MY BUSINESS AND WHAT I'VE BEEN ABLE TO ACCOMPLISH,
I'VE BEEN GIVEN A LITTLE BIT OF A VOICE AND THAT VOICE LETS ME
SPEAK FOR THOSE WHO DON'T HAVE A VOICE AND WHO HAVE A NEED.
SO IT'S NOT A BUSINESS THING. IT'S MORE A HUMAN THING.
IT'S A COMPASSION THING AND I THINK WE CAN LEAD BY EXAMPLE
AND OFFERING OUR COMMUNITY SOMETHING BACK.
IT'S A THANK YOU THANK YOU FOR LETTING ME BE ME AND OPERATING
IN YOUR AREA. SO WHETHER IT WAS THE MISSION
OR DISTRICT THREE I THINK LEADING BY EXAMPLE AND GIVING
BACK HELPS ME BE ME. SO AGAIN THANK YOU SO MUCH
AND IF I SMELL LIKE FOOD I'M SORRY WE'RE JUST KNOCKING OUT
SOME BURRITOS. I REALLY APPRECIATE THAT
CHOICE. WE GOT A LOT OF DONATIONS
AND THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THIS HONOR.
OH. >> DISTRICT TWO SUPERVISOR
CHERYL THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANTEL MIN COLLEAGUES TODAY I
AM HONORED TO COMMEND PIPER JOHNSON.
PIPER WILL YOU PLEASE COME UP TO THE LECTERN NOW?
>> PIPER BEFORE I GET INTO THIS I WANT TO THANK YOU FOR I THINK
MAYBE KNOCKING OFF OF SCHOOL A LITTLE EARLY TO BE HERE AND SO
THEORETICALLY I'D BE WORRIED THAT YOU'RE MISSING CLASS.
BUT AS WE'RE ALL ABOUT TO FIND OUT, I DON'T THINK THAT'S GOING
TO BE MUCH OF A PROBLEM FOR YOU PIPER IS A REMARKABLE STUDENT
AT SACRED HEART CATHEDRAL PREP IN DISTRICT TWO WHOSE
INNOVATION IS HELPING MAKE OUR COASTAL WATERS SAFER FOR
SWIMMERS, SURFERS AND MARINE LIFE AND FOR THOSE WHO DON'T
KNOW HER, PIPER LIVES IN THE RICHMOND DISTRICT IN DISTRICT
ONE WITH HER PARENTS JEREMIAH AND JULIE AND HER DOG TEDDY.
SHE GREW UP VISITING OCEAN BEACH AND IT WAS THOSE EARLY
EXPERIENCES THAT INSPIRED HER DEEP LOVE FOR THE OCEAN AFTER
LAST WINTER STORMS CAUSED SEWAGE RUNOFF ALONG THE COAST.
PIPER SAW FRIENDS FALL ILL AND NEIGHBORS AVOID THE BEACH.
BUT INSTEAD OF ACCEPTING THIS AS NORMAL, SHE DECIDED TO TAKE
ACTION AS PART OF SACRED HEART CATHEDRAL PREPS, INQUIRY
AND INNOVATION. I TO PROGRAM THIS PAST SEMESTER
PIPER DESIGNED AND BUILT A REAL TIME SEWAGE DETECTION SCENT
SENSOR THAT MEASURES DISSOLVED SOLIDS AND TURBIDITY THAT'S
CLOUDINESS IN OCEAN WATER. >> YES.
THANK YOU FOR TEACHING ME SOMETHING TO HER PROTOTYPE
PROVIDES READINGS IN SECONDS FAR FASTER THAN THE CITY'S LONG
TESTING CYCLE. IT CAN TRANSMIT DATA REMOTELY
AND EVENTUALLY IT WILL POWER A PUBLIC DASHBOARD TO HELP
BEACHGOERS ASSESS WATER QUALITY IN REAL TIME PAPER.
YOUR WORK EXEMPLIFIES WHAT CAN HAPPEN WHEN YOUNG PEOPLE ARE
EMPOWERED TO ENGAGE DIRECTLY WITH REAL WORLD PROBLEMS
AND CREATIVELY DELIVER TRANSFORMATIVE SOLUTIONS TO OUR
PRESSING ISSUES. AND IN A CITY FRANKLY THAT
LEADS THE WORLD IN INNOVATION YOU DEMONSTRATE HOW STEM
EDUCATION HAS HELPED MANY OF OUR STUDENTS JUST LIKE YOU STEP
INTO THAT LEGACY AND SHAPE THE FUTURE.
NOW BEYOND THIS PROJECT, PIPER IS ENGAGED IN GLOBAL
AND CLIMATE HEALTH WORK THROUGH UCSF INTERNSHIPS SERVICE
IN KENYA AND APPALACHIA AND A YEARLONG CAPSTONE WITH UCSF
CENTER FOR CLIMATE, HEALTH AND EQUITY.
>> AND IF YOU DON'T THINK THAT'S ENOUGH, PIPER IS ALSO A
TWO SPORT VARSITY ATHLETE IN SOCCER AND TENNIS AN AVID
BIOLOGY STUDENT, A DEDICATED VOLUNTEER AT DOG RESCUES
AND COMMUNITY GARDENS AND A CERRADO BAKER WITH A LOVE FOR
NONFICTION. BUT I WOULD BE REMISS IF I SAID
THIS WAS ONLY TO HONOR YOU TODAY BECAUSE WE ALSO MUST
HONOR YOUR PARENTS JEREMIAH JOHNSON AND JULIE BRANNIGAN
AND I TO MODERATOR DABNEY STANLEY FOR THEIR SUPPORT
IN NURTURING PIPER'S CURIOSITY ITY LEADERSHIP AND COMMITMENT
TO GIVING BACK. >> PIPER'S INNOVATION
AND SERVICE EMBODY THE SPIRIT OF SAN FRANCISCO BOLD IDEAS,
COMMUNITY DRIVEN SOLUTIONS AND A BELIEF THAT ONE PERSON
CAN TRULY MAKE A DIFFERENCE. SO TODAY PIPER WE CELEBRATE YOU
FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP, YOUR SCIENTIFIC CONTRIBUTIONS
AND THE EXAMPLE YOU SET NOT ONLY FOR YOUNG PEOPLE BUT FOR
ALL OF US ACROSS THE CITY. PIPER CONGRATULATIONS ON THIS
TREMENDOUS ACHIEVEMENT. WE'RE EXCITED TO SEE WHERE YOUR
TALENT AND DETERMINATION TAKE YOU NEXT.
AND I NOW INVITE YOU TO SAY A FEW WORDS.
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISORS SHERYL FOR THIS RECOGNITION.
I'VE ALWAYS BEEN INTERESTED IN MATH AND SCIENCE AND THE
WONDERFUL ACCESS TO NATURE WE HAVE AND THE COMMUNITY HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO AND THESE HAVE INSPIRED ME TO CREATE MY
PROJECT WHAT IT WAS. I LOOK FORWARD TO CONTINUING TO
WORK ON WAYS WE CAN MORE MEANINGFULLY AND RESPONSIBLY
ENJOY NATURE IN OUR ENVIRONMENT HERE IN THE CITY.
I ALSO WANT TO THANK SACRED HEART CATHEDRAL.
MY TEACHERS AND FELLOW STUDENTS WHO HAVE ALSO SUPPORTED ME
INSPIRED ME EVERY DAY. >> THANK YOU FOR SACRED HEART
CATHEDRAL. THANKS TO YOU.
>> ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR 3 P.M. SPECIAL
ORDERS WHICH I BELIEVE IS ITEMS 31 THROUGH 38.
>> YES. THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
ITEMS 31 THROUGH 34 TO BEGIN WITH IS A PUBLIC HEARING OF
PERSONS INTERESTED IN THE DETERMINED MOTION OF EXEMPTION
FROM ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW UNDER THE CALIFORNIA ENVIRONMENT
QUALITY ACT ISSUED AS A CATEGORICAL EXEMPTION BY THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT ON MAY 29TH 2025 FOR THE PROPOSED PROJECT
AT 350 EMBER DRIVE WHICH PROPOSES TO INSTALL A NEW AT&T
MACRO WIRELESS TELECOMMUNICATIONS FACILITY ON
AN APPROXIMATELY 104 FOOT TALL MONOPOLE CONSISTING OF 12 NEW
ANTENNAS AND NINE NEW REMOTE RADIO UNITS AND ANCILLARY
EQUIPMENT WITHIN THE PUBLIC ZONING DISTRICT AND OPEN SPACE
HEIGHT AND BULK DISTRICT. FOR THIS PUBLIC HEARING ITEM
32, 33 AND 34 ARE THE MOTIONS THAT EITHER AFFIRM THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT'S DETERMINATION OR CONDITIONALLY REVERSE THAT
DETERMINATION OR DIRECT THE PREPARATION OF FINDINGS FOR
ITEMS 35 THROUGH 30 EIGHT FOR THIS PUBLIC HEARING?
THIS IS FOR THOSE INTERESTED IN THE APPROVAL OF A
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION PURSUANT TO PLANNING CODE
SECTION 209.2303 AND 304 FOR THE PROPOSED PROJECT AT 350
AMBER DRIVE ISSUED BY THE PLANNING COMMISSION BY ITS
MOTION DATED SEPTEMBER 25TH, 2025 AGAIN TO INSTALL THE AT&T
MACRO WIRELESS COMMUNICATIONS FACILITY AS I DESCRIBED
AND ITEMS 30 637 AND 38 ARE THE MOTIONS THAT EITHER APPROVE THE
PLANNING COMMISSION'S DECISION THAT DISAPPROVE THE DECISION OR
REQUIRE THE PREPARATION OF FINDINGS.
>> ALL RIGHT. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK
COLLEAGUES BOTH THE APPELLANT AND PROJECT SPONSOR ARE
INTERESTED IN CONTINUING THIS ITEM.
WE OR THESE ITEMS WE'VE RECEIVED SIGNED CONTINUANCE
REQUESTS FROM BOTH. ALSO WAIVING THE STATUTORY
DEADLINES THAT WOULD OTHERWISE APPLY SO COLLEAGUES MIGHT I
HAVE A MOTION TO CONTINUE THESE APPEALS TO FEBRUARY 10TH 2026
MOVED BY MELGAR SECOND BY SAUDER AND WE WILL TAKE ACTION
MR. PRESIDENT. >> MOTION MR. PRESIDENT FOR YES
THAT'S RIGHT PUBLIC COMMENT. >> BUT FIRST WE NEED TO TO TAKE
PUBLIC COMMENT ON THE CONTINUANCES SO IF ANYONE WOULD
LIKE TO SPEAK ON THE CONTINUANCES YOU ARE WELCOME TO
COME FORWARD AND SPEAK AND LOOKS LIKE THERE'S NO ONE
COMING FORWARD. >> SO PUBLIC COMMENT ON THE
CONTINUANCE IS CLOSED AND SO MATT CLERK CAN YOU CALL THE
ROLL ON THE MOTION? >> YES, MR. PRESIDENT CAN YOU
JUST REMIND ME WHO MADE THE MOTION AND WHO SECONDED THE
MOTION? >> I BELIEVE IT WAS MADE BY
MELGAR. IT WAS SECONDED BY SÖDER.
IT WAS A MOTION TO CONTINUE THESE HEARINGS OPEN TO THE
FEBRUARY 10TH 26 BOARD OF SUPERVISORS MEETING.
>> THANK YOU. YES.
ON THE MOTION TO CONTINUE ITEMS 31 THROUGH 38 CONTINUE THESE
ITEMS OPEN TO FEBRUARY 10TH. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN HI MANDOLIN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL ABSENT
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER
I THERE ATTORNEYS WITHOUT OBJECTION THESE APPEAL HEARINGS
AND MOTIONS ARE CONTINUE TO OPEN TO FEBRUARY 10TH 2026
MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO COMMITTEE REPORTS PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER 39 ITEM 39 WAS CONSIDERED BY THE GOVERNMENT
AUDIT AND OVERSIGHT COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON
THURSDAY, DECEMBER 4TH, 2025 AND WAS FORWARDED AS A
COMMITTEE REPORT. ITEM 39 IS AN ORDINANCE TO
AUTHORIZE SETTLEMENT OF THE LAWSUIT FILED BY DAVON ANDERSON
BEVERLY L SWEENEY ON BEHALF OF THEMSELVES AND ALL OTHER
SIMILARLY SITUATED CURRENT AND FORMER EMPLOYEES AGAINST
THE CITY AND COUNTY FOR UP TO 20 MILLION.
>> THIS LAWSUIT INVOLVES AN EMPLOYMENT DISPUTE.
I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING I
BELIEVE ITEM 40 WAS NOT FORWARDED.
MADAM CLERK THAT IS CORRECT, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> SO CAN YOU PLEASE CALL ITEM 41 ITEM 41 THIS ITEM WAS
RECOMMENDED AS A COMMITTEE REPORT.
IT'S AN ORDINANCE TO DELEGATE AUTHORITY TO THE PUBLIC WORKS
DIRECTOR TO VACATE CERTAIN STREETS AND PUBLIC SERVICES
MINTS IN THE POTRERO HOPE S F PROJECT SITE GENERALLY BOUNDED
BY 26 WISCONSIN 23RD MISSOURI 22ND TEXAS 25TH AND CONNECTICUT
STREETS AND TO INCLUDE PORTIONS OF 22ND 23RD, 25TH, 26TH
ARKANSAS SHORES CONNECTICUT. DAKOTA.
TEXAS. MISSOURI AND WISCONSIN STREETS
TURNER TERRORISTS AND WATCHMEN WAY TO EXPEDITE IMPLEMENTATION
OF THE PROJECT AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS AND I
THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM STATES PRESIDENT WE HAVE A
DIFFERENT HOUSE OH, WE DO HAVE A DIFFERENT HOUSE.
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL THE ROLL AND ITEM 41 SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI RANDLEMAN I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUDER SORTER I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 42 ITEM 40 TO WAS RECOMMENDED BY THE
LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING
ON MONDAY DECEMBER 8TH. ITEM 14 TWO WAS RECOMMENDED AS
AMENDED BEARING THE SAME TITLE. IT'S A RESOLUTION TO DECLARE
THE INTENTION OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO VACATE PORTIONS
OF HAYS STREET, GRIFFITH STREET AND BANCROFT AVENUE FOR THE
DEVELOPMENT OF THE FIRE DEPARTMENT TRAINING FACILITY AT
1236 CARROLL AVENUE AND TO SET A HEARING DATE FOR ALL PERSONS
INTERESTED IN THE PROPOSED VACATION OF SAID STREET AREAS.
AND THIS IS WHEN I THINK WE CAN TAKE SAME HOUSE SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 43.
ITEM 43 THIS ITEM WAS IS A MOTION TO APPROVE A FINAL MAP
NUMBER 10857AT COMMERCIAL UNIT CONDOMINIUM PROJECT LOCATED AT
13 ZERO ONE AND 1341 EVANS AVENUE AND TO MAKE THE
APPROPRIATE FINDINGS THIS ITEM WAS RECOMMENDED AS A COMMITTEE
REPORT AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
>> MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO A ROLL CALL FOR INTRODUCTIONS.
>> YES. FIRST UP TO INTRODUCE NEW
BUSINESS SUPERVISOR MY WORK COLLEAGUES THROUGHOUT THE YEAR
WE WATCHED AS OTHER CITIES EXPERIENCED AN UNIMAGINABLE
TAKEOVER BY THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT AND WE LIKE OTHER
CITIES FELT ILL PREPARED FOR THAT EVENTUALITY.
WE HEARD FIRSTHAND OF THE WORKERS WHO PLAN TO STAY HOME.
THE STUDENTS WHO MISS CLASS DROP OFF AND OUR OWN CITY
EMPLOYEES WHO FELT THEY WERE LOOKING OVER THEIR SHOULDER AS
THEY WENT TO WORK. >> WE WERE ON THE VERGE OF
EXPERIENCING SOMETHING TERRIBLE AND IT WAS THE FEAR AND PANIC
OF OUR NEIGHBORS THAT PROMPTED MY OFFICE TO TAKE ACTION.
WE WORKED WITH OUR DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEYS WHO TOOK A CREATIVE
APPROACH TO LEARN FROM OTHER CITIES FOR SOLUTIONS BECAUSE
HERE'S WHAT WE KNOW WHEREVER LARGE SCALE IMMIGRATION
ENFORCEMENT HAPPENS, DISRUPTION FOLLOWS.
FAMILIES STAY AWAY FROM SCHOOLS.
SENIORS MISSED THEIR MEDICAL APPOINTMENTS, BUSINESSES CLOSE
OR REDUCE HOURS AND WORKERS MISS SHIFTS ALL OF WHICH
CONTRIBUTE TO LOST REVENUE, LOCAL ECONOMIC DECLINE AND A
REDUCTION IN PUBLIC SAFETY. SO TODAY, COLLEAGUES, I'M
INTRODUCING LEGISLATION AS AN ORDINANCE IN WHICH WE FOUND A
PIECE OF THE CITY ADMIN CODE THAT WE COULD STRENGTHEN WITH
THIS LEGISLATION MAKING IT THE FIRST OF ITS KIND IN THE NATION
BECAUSE THESE ARE IMPACTS WE SIMPLY CANNOT AFFORD.
>> AND TODAY THE ORDINANCE WE ARE INTRODUCING WILL AMEND
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE SECTION 4.19 TO ACCOMPLISH THE
FOLLOWING ONE PROHIBIT ANY ENTITY FROM COMMANDEERING CITY
PROPERTY FOR USE THAT WOULD DISRUPT CITY OPERATIONS,
DISCOURAGE ACCESS TO CITY SERVICES OR CONFLICT WITH A
CITY PURPOSE. PROHIBIT CITY STAFF FROM
ALLOWING ANYONE TO USE CITY OWNED PROPERTY IN A WAY THAT
WOULD INTERFERE WITH CITY OPERATIONS OR HINDER PUBLIC
ACCESS TO CITY SERVICES. >> STAFF MAY FACE DISCIPLINARY
ACTION FOR VIOLATIONS. >> THIRD, CLARIFY THAT THE USE
OF REAL OR PERSONAL PROPERTY TO ASSIST IN THE ENFORCEMENT OF
FEDERAL IMMIGRATION LAW IS NOT A CITY PURPOSE.
>> AND LASTLY, AUTHORIZE THE CITY ATTORNEY TO TAKE LEGAL
ACTION AGAINST ANY ENTITY ENGAGED IN UNLAWFUL OR
UNAUTHORIZED USE OF CITY PROPERTY BECAUSE THIS IS AS
IMPORTANT BECAUSE PUBLIC SAFETY IS OUR TOP PRIORITY IN SAN
FRANCISCO'S OWN PUBLIC SAFETY PROGRESS WHICH INCLUDES A
NEARLY 30% CITYWIDE DECREASE IN CRIME RELIES HEAVILY ON
COMMUNITY TRUST AND COOPERATION WITH OUR IMMIGRANT COMMUNITY
REPRESENTING A LARGE PORTION OF SAN FRANCISCANS.
WE CANNOT BLUR THE LINE BETWEEN LOCAL GOVERNMENT AND FEDERAL
IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT. IT IS OUR JOB TO DELIVER
SERVICES. IT IS OUR JOB TO MAKE RESIDENTS
FEEL THEY CAN TRUST US AND IT IS OUR JOB TO MAKE SURE THIS
CITY WORKS FOR EVERYONE OUR CITY THRIVES WHEN EVERY
RESIDENT FEELS THEY CAN ACCESS CITY SERVICES FREELY WHETHER
THAT'S DROPPING CHILDREN OFF AT SCHOOL, GOING TO THE DOCTOR,
REPORTING A CRIME OR COMING TO CITY HALL FOR A MARRIAGE
LICENSE. >> THIS ORDINANCE ASSURES OUR
CITY'S FACILITIES REMAIN ACCESSIBLE, IT STRENGTHENS OUR
LOCAL CONTROL AND IT ENSURES THAT NO MATTER WHAT WE AS THE
CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO CAN SERVE THE PUBLIC.
I'D LIKE TO THANK DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY JOHN, A CLERK FOR
DRAFTING THIS LEGISLATION WITH MY LEGISLATIVE DIRECTOR SAM
LOGAN AND CHIEF OF STAFF JESSICA GUTIERREZ.
GARCIA AND MY OFFICE WORKING ON THIS LEGISLATION AS WELL.
I'D ALSO LIKE TO THANK S.F. RISING A24 MISSION ACTION
CHINESE FOR AFFIRMATIVE ACTION S.F. LATINO PARITY AND EQUITY
COALITION AND OTHER IMMIGRANT RIGHTS ADVOCATES GROUPS FOR
THEIR PARTNERSHIP AND FEEDBACK ON THIS LEGISLATION.
>> AND FINALLY I'D LIKE TO THANK SUPERVISOR CHEYENNE CHEN
FOR HER EARLY CO-AUTHORSHIP AND PARTNERSHIP ON THIS
LEGISLATION AND SUPERVISORS MELGAR, SADR FIELDER AND WALTON
FOR YOUR EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP AS WELL.
>> NEXT COLLEAGUES, I WOULD LIKE TO UPDATE EVERYONE ON
WHAT'S GOING ON AT THE BAY AREA AIR QUALITY MANAGEMENT DISTRICT
BOARD OF DIRECTORS WHICH I SERVED ON WHEN SUPERVISOR
WALTON EARLIER THIS YEAR WE APPROVED STAFFING CHANGES THAT
WILL HELP TACKLE THE PERMITTING BACKLOG THAT THE AIR DISTRICT
HAS BEEN SUFFERING FROM. THIS IS PART OF AN ONGOING
PROCESS TO ANALYZE THE ISSUES THAT AFFECT THE PACE OF
PERMITTING EVERYTHING FROM CLARITY OF RULES TO THE
DIFFICULTY OF REGULATING NEW TECHNOLOGIES.
>> ADDITIONALLY, IN EARLY 2026 THE AIR DISTRICT WILL HOST
WORKSHOPS AROUND AMENDMENTS OF THE BUILDING APPLIANCE RULES
THAT PASSED IN 2023. >> THESE RULES WILL REQUIRE NEW
MODELS OF APPLIANCES BE INSTALLED IN THE REGION TO NOT
GENERATE HARMFUL NITROGEN OXIDE POLLUTION.
>> THEY TAKE EFFECT IN 2027 FOR RESIDENTIAL WATER HEATERS, 2029
FOR FURNACES AND SO ON. AMENDMENTS ARE BEING CONSIDERED
TO CENTER AROUND LOW INCOME AND SMALL BUSINESS EXEMPTIONS
GRANTING EXTRA TIME FOR HOMES NEEDING MAJOR UPGRADES
AND EXTENDING TIMELINES AROUND THE SALE OF SMALLER WATER
HEATERS. LOOK FORWARD TO CONTINUING TO
ENGAGE ON THIS MEANINGFUL RULEMAKING.
THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M INTRODUCING AN ORDINANCE TO
MODERNIZE AND STRENGTHEN SAN FRANCISCO'S FILM INCENTIVE
PROGRAM. SAN FRANCISCO'S LANDMARK
SCENERY AND HISTORY HAVE BEEN FEATURED IN COUNTLESS FILMS
INCLUDING VERTIGO, MRS. DOUBTFIRE, INVASION OF THE BODY
SNATCHERS AND MORE. OUR CITY HAS ALWAYS PRIDED
ITSELF ON OUR STORYTELLING AND ART AND FILMS ARE A VITAL
PART OF OUR ARTISTIC AND CULTURAL LEGACY.
HOWEVER, IN MORE RECENT YEARS FEWER PRODUCTIONS ARE CHOOSING
TO FILM IN SAN FRANCISCO. EVEN PROJECTS SET IN SAN
FRANCISCO ONLY SHOOT IN THE CITY FOR VERY SHORT PERIODS OF
TIME. >> THE S.F. FILM COMMISSION HAS
LONG RECOGNIZED THE NEED TO BRING PRODUCTIONS BACK TO SAN
FRANCISCO AND ESTABLISHED AN INCENTIVE PROGRAM TO DO THAT
IN 2006. >> HOWEVER, OUR FILM INCENTIVE
PROGRAM FACES COMPETITION FROM OVER 120 OTHER INCENTIVE
PROGRAMS ACROSS THE GLOBE. MANY OF WHICH OFFER BETTER
BENEFITS THAN OURS. PRODUCTIONS THUS OFTEN CHOOSE
TO GO ELSEWHERE. >> FILM INCENTIVE PROGRAMS
PROVIDE FINANCIAL BENEFITS TO FILM, TELEVISION AND COMMERCIAL
PRODUCTIONS IN ORDER TO ENCOURAGE THEM TO SHOOT LOCALLY
AND GENERATE ECONOMIC ACTIVITY. >> OUR CURRENT PROGRAM ONLY
OFFERS A REBATE FOR CITY DEPARTMENT FEES AND TO QUALIFY
PRODUCTIONS NEED TO SHOOT 55 TO 65% OF THEIR PROJECTS IN SAN
FRANCISCO. THIS REBATE IS ADDITIONALLY
CAPPED AT $600,000 FOR CITY FEES ONLY.
>> THESE INCENTIVES ARE QUITE LIMITED IN COMPARISON TO OTHER
INCENTIVE PROGRAMS AND OUR INABILITY TO CONSISTENTLY
ATTRACT PRODUCTIONS MEANS THAT WE ALSO CANNOT OFFER
NON-FINANCIAL INCENTIVES TO FILM HERE SUCH AS A DEDICATED
PRODUCTION STAGE OR INFRASTRUCTURE DEVELOPMENT.
>> THIS ORDINANCE SEEKS TO UPDATE OUR FILM INCENTIVE
PROGRAMS TO BE MORE MODERN AND COMPETITIVE.
IT INCREASES THE REBATE AMOUNT AVAILABLE TO PRODUCTIONS,
LOWERS THE MINIMUM SPENDING AND ELIGIBILITY REQUIREMENTS TO
QUALIFY FOR A REBATE, MODIFIES DAILY USE FEE EXEMPTIONS
AND UPDATES AND CLARIFIES SEVERAL DEFINITIONS
AND PRODUCTION GUIDELINES. A SINGLE PRODUCTION CAN INJECT
MILLIONS OF DOLLARS INTO THE LOCAL ECONOMY AND DIRECT
SPENDING. THE AVERAGE LOCATION SHOOT ADDS
$670,000 AND 1500 JOBS A DAY INTO THE LOCAL ECONOMY FOR
EVERY DOLLAR OUR CITY HAS REBATED FOR PAST FILM SHOOTS
PRODUCTIONS HAVE SPENT $12.68 LOCALLY AND CONTRIBUTED
SIGNIFICANTLY TO SAN FRANCISCO'S ECONOMY IN NUMEROUS
WAYS INCLUDING EMPLOYING 16,000 PLUS LOCAL CREW AND ACTORS
PAYING $26 MILLION IN WAGES TO LOCAL CREW AND TALENT
AND SPENDING OVER $68 MILLION IN GOODS AND SERVICES.
THE SAN FRANCISCO FILM COMMISSION HAS HEARD FROM MANY
PRODUCTIONS MAJOR STUDIOS AND OTHER STAKEHOLDERS THAT ARE
EAGER TO SHOOT HERE AND EXCITED TO INVEST IN OUR CITY'S
CREATIVE INFRASTRUCTURE. AND THEY BELIEVE THESE UPDATES
HAVE THE POTENTIAL TO INCREASE OVERALL PRODUCTION BY UP TO 25%
AND CAN HELP ENSURE THAT SAN FRANCISCO CAN GENERATE LONG
TERM ECONOMIC GROWTH AND INVESTMENT REMAIN
COMPETITIVE IN THE GLOBAL CREATIVE ECONOMY AND MAINTAIN
OUR CULTURAL LEGACY. STRENGTHENING OUR INCENTIVES
SIGNALS TO THE INDUSTRY THAT SAN FRANCISCO IS SERIOUS ABOUT
ATTRACTING PRODUCTIONS AND COMPETING WITH OTHER
REGIONS. I WANT TO THANK MONISHA FETTA
AND SOPHIA LA CASTRO FROM FILM S.F..
ALESSANDRA LOZANO FROM THE OFFICE OF ECONOMIC
AND WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT AND LURIE AND LAUREN CURREY
FROM THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE FOR THEIR WORK ON THE
LEGISLATION. I ALSO WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR
CHAN FOR HER EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP.
AND I WANT TO THANK GRACE WANG AND CALVIN IN MY OFFICE FOR
THEIR WORK AS WELL. I ALSO HAVE AN UPDATE FROM THE
TRANSBAY JOINT POWERS AUTHORITY BOARD WHERE I SERVE AS VICE
CHAIR, THE JPA AND THE PORTAL PROJECT HAVE HAD A PRODUCTIVE
FALL AT THE BOARD'S OCTOBER MEETING WE RECEIVED A
PRESENTATION REGARDING THE ENVISIONED REDEVELOPMENT OF THE
FOURTH AND KING RAIL YARDS TO BE SERVED BY IN THE FUTURE BY
THE PORTAL'S NEW UNDERGROUND FOURTH AND TOWNSEND STATION THE
CENTER OF A GROWING TRANSIT ORIENTED NEIGHBORHOOD
AND REGIONAL TRANSIT HUB. IN EARLY NOVEMBER T.J. STAFF
WENT TO SACRAMENTO TO MEET WITH THE CALIFORNIA STATE
TRANSPORTATION AGENCY AND LEGISLATIVE STAFF.
IN THE YEAR AHEAD WE'LL BE WORKING TO LEVERAGE THE STATE'S
RECENT ENACTMENT IN SEPTEMBER OF THE EXTENDED CAP AND TRADE
PROGRAM WHICH IS PLANNED TO PROVIDE MORE THAN A BILLION
DOLLARS TO THE PORTAL PROJECT TO CAPTURE THESE FUNDS
AND SECURE FEDERAL COMMITMENT IN THE COMING YEARS.
WE'LL ALSO BE CONSIDERING AN EXTENSION OR EXPANSION OF LOCAL
FUNDING SOURCES INCLUDING THOSE DRIVEN BY ONGOING DEVELOPMENT
AROUND SALESFORCE TRANSIT CENTER.
ALSO THIS FALL TGP STAFF WELCOME THE NEW CEO OF THE
CALIFORNIA HIGH SPEED RAIL AUTHORITY FOR THE TOUR OF THE
TRANSIT CENTER AND THE AGENCY'S SENIOR STAFF EXCHANGED LESSONS
LEARNED AND STRATEGIES FOR ADVANCING THE PROJECT AS THE
NORTHERN TERMINUS OF THE STATE'S HIGH SPEED SYSTEM.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU ,MR. PRESIDENT.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
I JUST HAVE AN UPDATE IN MY CAPACITY AS A MEMBER OF THE
METROPOLITAN TRANSPORTATION COMMISSION.
LAST THE MTA BAG PUTS OUT A POT OF MONEY THAT WE USE TO
INCENTIVIZE FOLKS IN THE REGION TO MEET AT REGIONAL GOALS.
THOSE GOALS ARE BALANCED AND MUTUALLY REINFORCING WITH
THE COUNTY GOALS. WE HAVE SPENT THE LAST COUPLE
OF MONTHS IN HONING DOWN ON AN UPDATED SET OF PRINCIPLES TO
PUT OUT THE NEXT SET OF GRANTS FOR THE ONE BAY AREA GRANT
PROGRAM WHICH IS IN ITS FOURTH REITERATION.
THE PRINCIPLES THAT HAVE BEEN PROPOSED IS TO PROVIDE A
FLEXIBLE FUNDING SOURCE TO DELIVER LOCAL PRIORITY PROJECTS
THAT SUPPORT BAY AREA OBJECTIVES WITHIN EMPHASIS ON
LOCAL ROAD SAFETY, COMPLETE STREETS AND A STATE OF GOOD
REPAIR AND TO INCENTIVIZE LOCAL PARTNER AGENTS TO ADVANCE
PLANNED BAY AREA GOALS WHICH ARE IMPLEMENTING EFFECTIVE
REGIONAL INITIATIVES AND SERVICES WITH AN EMPHASIS
ON INCLUSIVE COMMUNITIES SUSTAINABILITY AND AN OPTIMIZED
EXPERIENCE FOR ALL TRAVELERS TO ADVANCE LOCAL AGENCIES PROGRESS
TOWARDS REGIONAL GOALS THROUGH COORDINATED PLANNING
AND TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE AND TO ADDRESS MULTIJURISDICTIONAL
CHALLENGES AND IMPROVE KEY CORRIDORS WITH REGIONAL
LEADERSHIP AND STRATEGIC SUPPORT.
WE HAVE SEEN A REDUCTION BECAUSE OF FEDERAL SOURCE
REDUCTIONS IN THIS POT OF MONEY BUT IT IS APPROXIMATELY $800
MILLION OVER THE NEXT FOUR YEARS FOR THE REGION.
THAT COMPARES TO ABOUT 900 MILLIONS IN THE ONE BAY AREA
GRANT THREE PROCESS WHICH IS WHAT PRECEDED THIS ONE.
SOME OF THE THINGS THAT HAVE BEEN DISCUSSED WITH THE NINE
COUNTY BAY AREA REPRESENTATIVES THAT MAKE UP THE MTC RIGHT NOW
ARE A SET OF PRINCIPLES THAT SUPPORT TRANSIT ORIENTED
COMMUNITIES INCLUDING RENTER PROTECTIONS FOR ANY NEW
DEVELOPMENT AND THE DEEP NEED FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING
FINANCING. STAY TUNED.
WE THINK THAT WE WILL BE DONE WITH ALL THE CONVERSATIONS
AND VOTING SO THAT WE CAN PUT OUT THIS MONEY BY THE SUMMER.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR. SUPERVISOR SAUDER.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE TWO ITEMS TO INTRODUCE.
FIRST, I'M INTRODUCING A REQUEST FOR A BUDGET
AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYSIS ON UNDERUTILIZED SIZE PUBLIC
PROPERTY. >> WE ARE HOPING THIS REPORT
CAN SHED LIGHT ON THE MANY CITY OR STATE OWNED SITES IN SAN
FRANCISCO THAT ARE DORMANT NOT SERVING THEIR FULL CAPACITY OR
INTENDED USE OR MAYBE CONSIDERED SURPLUS LAND.
>> WHEN TAKING INTO ACCOUNT CITY COLLEGE AND THE SCHOOL
DISTRICT PROPERTIES, WE ANTICIPATE SOME 600 PROPERTIES
ARE IN THE PUBLIC INVENTORY OF SITES AND WE ANTICIPATE WE
EXPECT THAT SOME 50 OF THESE PROPERTIES COULD BE CONSIDERED
SURPLUS OR UNDERUTILIZED. WE WANT THIS REPORT TO EXPLORE
ALL POSSIBLE OUTCOMES FOR THESE PROPERTIES.
>> IN SOME CASES THEY MAY BE ABLE TO BE ACTIVATED AND SERVE
A COMMUNITY NEED. FOR EXAMPLE THERE IS AN S.F.
USD SITE IN THE LOWER POLK NEIGHBORHOOD THAT IS CURRENTLY
BEING USED AS A PARKING LOT AND THIS DOESN'T FEEL LIKE THE
HIGHEST USE FOR A NEIGHBORHOOD THAT HAS BEEN ASKING FOR YEARS
FOR MORE OPEN SPACE. >> IN OTHER CASES THE LANDS MAY
BE POTENTIAL DEVELOPMENT SITES FOR NEW HOMES.
WE ALSO SHOULDN'T RULE OUT OPPORTUNITIES TO LEASE OR SELL
PROPERTIES THAT CAN SUPPORT OUR CITY'S CHALLENGING BUDGET.
I LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING WITH THE BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE
ANALYSTS. OUR REAL ESTATE DIVISION
AND OTHERS TO PRODUCE THIS REPORT AND ENSURE WE ARE USING
OUR PUBLIC PROPERTIES FOR THEIR HIGHEST NEED.
>> NEXT I AM INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION TO UPDATE
PERMISSIONS AND ACTIVATE MAIDEN LANE AN ICONIC ALLEYWAY
IN UNION SQUARE MAIDEN LANE HAS BEEN CLOSED TO VEHICULAR
TRAFFIC DURING THE DAYTIME FOR MANY YEARS AND THERE HAS BEEN A
RESOLUTION AND PUBLIC WORKS ORDER FOR THE ALLEY DATING BACK
TO 1973. FOR DECADES THIS BOARD HAS
UNDERSTOOD THE BENEFIT OF ALLOWING THE UNION SQUARE
IMPROVEMENT DISTRICT. NOW THE UNION SQUARE ALLIANCE
TO PROGRAM LANE WITH TABLES, CHAIRS AND EVENTS.
THE ACTIVATION OF MAIDEN LANE ACTUALLY DATES BACK TO THE
1940S WITH THE ESTABLISHMENT OF THE ANNUAL SPRING COMES TO
MAIDEN LANE FESTIVAL WHICH SAW THE TWO BLOCKS ADORNED WITH
FLOWING STRINGS OF FLOWERS ACROSS THE ALLEY.
THEN IN MAY 1955 A THREE HOUR PEDESTRIAN PERIOD BEGAN AND SAW
4000 VISITORS CRAM INTO THE LANE TO ENJOY A PERFORMANCE BY
THE SAN FRANCISCO MUNICIPAL BAND AND A SPEECH FROM
MAYOR ELMER E ROBINSON. >> MIDLAND WAS ONCE CALLED ONE
OF THE FINEST SHOPPING STREETS IN AMERICA AND WAS PRAISED BY
JANE JACOBS FOR ITS QUOTE INTIMACY CHEERFULNESS
AND SPONTANEITY. IT IS HOME TO THE ONLY FRANK
LLOYD WRIGHT DESIGNED BUILDING IN ALL OF SAN FRANCISCO.
THIS RESOLUTION IS THE NEXT STEP IN MAIDEN LANE'S STORIED
HISTORY AND WILL PUT THE STREET CLOSURE AUTHORITY WITH THE FIRM
TO ALLOW STREET ACTIVATIONS INTO THE EVENING HOURS
AND ALLOW THE UNION SQUARE ALLIANCE TO DO ART
INSTALLATIONS AND MORE EVENTS. THIS BUILDS ON THE MOMENTUM
IN UNION SQUARE WHICH IN THE PAST MONTH ALONE HAS SEEN THE
OPENING OF A NEW BOOKSTORE A NEW TOY STORE, SUCCESSFUL THIRD
THURSDAY CONCERTS ON ELLIS AND A FLURRY OF HOLIDAY
ACTIVITY. I WANT TO THANK TITA BELL IN MY
OFFICE FOR HER HARD WORK TO GET THIS READY FOR INTRODUCTION TO
JOHN MCCLYMONT IN THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE AND TO THE
UNION SQUARE ALLIANCE FOR THEIR PARTNERSHIP ON THIS AND THEIR
EVERYDAY WORK. AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR SAUDER SUPERVISOR
CHERYL THANK YOU. >> SUBMIT.
SUPERVISOR WALTON. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH MADAM
CLERK. FIRST I WOULD LIKE TO BE ADDED
AS A CO-SPONSOR TO PRESIDENT MENDELSOHN'S FILM INCENTIVE
PROGRAM TO COLLEAGUES TODAY. I DO HAVE AN IN MEMORIAM FOR
THE TRAGIC LOSS OF OUR FELLOW CITY WORKER ALBERTO RANGEL WHO
MADE THE ULTIMATE SACRIFICE WHILE SERVING THE PEOPLE OF SAN
FRANCISCO WITH COMPASSION AND DEDICATION.
ALBERTO WAS 51 AND A CHERISHED SAN FRANCISCO GENERAL HOSPITAL
AND UCSF SOCIAL WORKER WHOSE LIFE WAS DEDICATED TO HEALING
SERVICE AND COMMUNITY OUT OF BERTO PASSED AWAY ON SATURDAY
DECEMBER 7TH. AFTER SUCCUMBING TO INJURIES HE
SUFFERED DURING THE VIOLENT ATTACK AT SAN FRANCISCO GENERAL
ON DECEMBER 4TH. DESPITE THE HEROIC EFFORTS OF
HIS COLLEAGUES IN WARD 86 AND THE EMERGENCY TRAUMA
AND INTENSIVE CARE TEAMS AT GENERAL, HE DID NOT RECOVER.
HIS DEATH HAS SHAKEN THE ENTIRE CITY AND HAS LEFT DEEP GRIEF
ACROSS UCSF. S.F. GENERAL THE SAN FRANCISCO
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH AND AMONG ALL WHO KNEW
AND LOVED HIM. ALBERTO SERVED AS A LICENSED
MARRIAGE AND FAMILY THERAPIST WITH UCSF AND WAS ASSIGNED TO
WARD 86 THE HIV CARE UNIT WHERE HE BROUGHT COMPASSION, PATIENCE
AND DIGNITY TO SOME OF THE MOST VULNERABLE MEMBERS OF OUR
COMMUNITY. HIS CAREER SPANNED MORE THAN
TWO DECADES AND INCLUDED SERVICE AT THE MISSION
NEIGHBORHOOD HEALTH CENTER AND THE TRAUMA RECOVERY CENTER
AT PARNASSUS. HIS WORK FOCUSED ON TRAUMA,
DEPRESSION AND ANXIETY. MULTI-ETHNIC AND LGBTQ PLUS
ISSUES. AND HE PROVIDED CRITICAL
SUPPORT TO CLIENTS SEEKING ASYLUM TO ESCAPE PERSECUTION
AND VIOLENCE IN THEIR HOME COUNTRIES.
HE WAS ALSO A GIFTED ARTIST WHO PORTRAYED EVERYDAY SCENES
GROUNDED IN HIS CULTURAL IDENTITY.
HIS ARTWORK WAS DISPLAYED THROUGHOUT THE CITY HE LOVED
AND HE SHARED HIS CREATIVITY AS GENEROUSLY AS HE SHARED HIS
CARE. >> IN AN ONLINE BIOGRAPHY,
ALBERTO WROTE THAT GROWING UP AS A GAY IDENTIFIED FIRST
GENERATION LATINO FROM MEXICO IN IOWA TAUGHT HIM HOW LIFE
CHANGING SUPPORT AND COMMUNITY CAN BE.
>> HE SAID THAT BEING OF SERVICE WAS CENTRAL TO WHO HE
WAS AND THAT IT WAS A PRIVILEGE TO ACCOMPANY INDIVIDUALS TOWARD
HEALING AND WELLNESS. THOSE WORDS CAPTURED THE HEART
OF THE PERSON SO MANY ADMIRED. OUT ALBERTO WILL BE REMEMBERED
FOR HIS GENTLE SPIRIT. THE RESPECT HE SHOWED EVERY
PATIENT AND HIS ABILITY TO SEE THE HUMANITY IN EACH PERSON HE
ENCOUNTERED. >> HIS COLLEAGUES SPEAK OF HIS
JOY, HIS PERSONALITY, HIS DEEP EMPATHY AND THE INTEGRITY HE
CARRIED INTO EVERY ROOM. THIS WAS DEFINITELY EVIDENT BY
THE NUMBER OF PEOPLE I WITNESSED FIRSTHAND AT HIS
VIGIL LAST NIGHT AT SAN FRANCISCO GENERAL.
A NATIVE OF MUSCATINE, IOWA, ALBERTO BUILT HIS LIFE IN SAN
FRANCISCO WITH HIS HUSBAND OF 20 YEARS.
HE IS SURVIVED BY HIS HUSBAND STUART.
HIS PARENTS SIBLINGS, NIECES AND NEPHEWS.
AND THE COUNTLESS PATIENTS, COWORKERS AND FRIENDS WHOSE
LIVES HE TOUCHED. AS WE CONTINUE TO PROCESS THE
PAIN OF THIS TRAGEDY, MAY WE HONOR ALBERTO BY RECOMMITTING
OURSELVES TO THE SAFETY OF OUR FRONTLINE PUBLIC HEALTH WORKERS
AND TO THE COMPASSION AND EQUITY HE MODEL EVERY DAY.
I PRESENT AMENDMENT. I WOULD ALSO LIKE TO ADD THIS
MEMORIAM ON BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD.
I KNOW SUPERVISOR FIELDER HAD SOME WORK SHE WANTED TO SHARE
AS WELL. LET'S SEE THAT ON BEHALF OF THE
FULL BOARD UNLESS THEIR OBJECTIONS KEPT SUPERVISOR
FIELDER. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WALTON
SUPERVISOR. >> SUPERVISOR.
YES. SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR WALTON
FOR MAKING THIS ON BEHALF OF THE WHOLE BOARD.
IT'S JUST DEVASTATING. ANY TIME SOMEONE IN OUR CITY
WORKFORCE WHO SHOWS UP EVERY DAY WITH A SELFLESSNESS THAT
REALLY MAKES THIS CITY BEAUTIFUL FEARED FOR THE SAFETY
AT ALL. AND SO I JUST THINK IT'S IT'S
REALLY JUST IT'S JUST PURELY DEVASTATING.
AND I WANT TO GIVE MY HEARTFELT CONDOLENCES IS TO THE FRIENDS
AND FAMILY FOREMOST OF ALBERTO AND AS WELL OF COURSE THE AS OF
GENERAL STAFF AND COMMUNITY THAT GIVE THEMSELVES SO MUCH
EVERY DAY. >> EVERYONE DESERVES FEEL SAFE
AT THEIR PLACE OF WORK AND THAT GOES FOR ALL CITY EMPLOYEES
WHETHER YOU'RE A POLICEMAN, FIREFIGHTER, A NURSE, A SOCIAL
WORKER. >> AND I'M JUST SO TOUCHED BY
THE HUNDREDS OF PEOPLE THAT CAME OUT TO HIS VIGIL AND THE
OUTPOURING OF SUPPORT. WARD 86 IS A SPECIAL PLACE
IN THIS CITY'S HISTORY AND THEY SERVE NOT ONLY HIV, UH FOLKS
BUT ALSO SOME OF THE MOST VULNERABLE PEOPLE IN THE CITY.
AND THAT REQUIRES A LOT OF RESILIENCE TO COME IN TO WORK
EVERY DAY. AND SO I JUST WANT TO THANK
REGGIE WALTON AND SEND MY MY CONDOLENCES TO THE WHOLE
COMMUNITY. THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. AND COLLEAGUES, AS A FOLLOW UP
TO THIS I AM REQUESTING A LETTER OF INQUIRY FROM THE
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH AND THE SHERIFF'S DEPARTMENT
REQUESTING A GENERAL OVERVIEW OF THE INTERNAL INVESTIGATION
AND THE INDEPENDENT SECURITY REVIEW INCLUDING EXPECTED
TIMELINES FOR COMPLETION AND HOW FINDINGS WILL BE
COMMUNICATED TO STAFF AND THE BOARD.
A SUMMARY OF EXISTING SAFETY AND SECURITY PROTOCOLS IS
CURRENTLY IN PLACE AT S.F. GENERAL AND CLINICS AND AN
EXPLANATION OF WHICH PROTOCOLS ARE BEING STRENGTHENED OR NEWLY
IMPLEMENTED IN RESPONSE TO THIS INCIDENT.
>> A DESCRIPTION OF THE IMMEDIATE SAFETY ACTIONS TAKEN
BY BOTH DEPARTMENTS INCLUDING CHANGES TO BUILDING ACCESS
SCREENING PROCEDURES AND ONSITE SECURITY PRESENCE.
A PLAN OUTLINING HOW H AND THE SHERIFF'S DEPARTMENT WILL
COORDINATE GOING FORWARD TO ENSURE CONSISTENT RELIABLE
SAFETY PRACTICES ACROSS ALL DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH
FACILITIES. >> AND A DESCRIPTION OF THE
SHORT TERM AND LONG TERM IMPROVEMENTS UNDER
CONSIDERATION TO ENHANCE WORKER SAFETY ACROSS HOSPITALS
AND CLINICS INCLUDING TRAINING, COMMUNICATION INFRASTRUCTURE
AND EMERGENCY RESPONSE PROCEDURES.
AND I DO KNOW THAT THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH HAS
ALREADY INSTITUTED SOME IMMEDIATE CHANGES AND I LOOK
FORWARD TO HEARING FROM THE DEPARTMENT IN TERMS OF WHAT
THEY'RE GOING TO DO IMMEDIATELY AND IN THE LONG TERM.
>> AND THE LAST THING I DO HAVE AN UPDATE FROM CALTRAIN.
I SHARED THIS AT TODAY'S TRANSPORTATION AUTHORITY
MEETING. BUT I ALSO WANT TO PROVIDE AN
UPDATE HERE AT THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS MEETING.
>> WE'VE HAD A CONVERSATION AROUND GOVERNANCE IN REGARD TO
CALTRAIN FOR DECADES. ORIGINALLY SAM TRANS WAS NAMED
AS THE MANAGING AGENCY OF CALTRAIN IN PERPETUITY.
FROM ONSET IN MY TENURE ON CALTRAIN I KNEW THAT WAS
IRRESPONSIBLE AND AN ANTI GOVERNANCE MODEL THAT HAD TO
CHANGE PRIOR TO MY ARRIVAL ON THE JP BOARD J P B BOARD.
WE DID NOT HAVE OUR OWN COUNSEL FOR CALTRAIN.
WE ALSO DID NOT HAVE THE AUTHORITY TO HIRE AND FIRE THE
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR. WHICH ARE BOTH COMPLETELY
IRRESPONSIBLE, BOTH FOR GOVERNANCE AND FOR ENSURING
THAT SAN FRANCISCO HAD EQUITABLE DECISION MAKING WHEN
IT CAME TO CALTRAIN. FAST FORWARD WE MADE THOSE
CHANGES AND ALSO AGREED AFTER PASSAGE OF MEASURE R WE WILL
CONTINUE TO ADDRESS ISSUES OF GOVERNANCE MAINLY THE MANAGING
AGENCY ISSUE THE ISSUE OF SHARED SERVICES AGREEMENT
SALARY ORDINANCE AND CONDUCT AN AUDIT OF THE RAIL, NONE OF
WHICH HAVE HAPPENED. >> WE SAN FRANCISCO AND SANTA
CLARA COUNTY PAID OFF ALL BALANCES OWED TO SAM TRAINS
IN ORDER TO BRING EVERYONE UP TO A LEVEL PLAYING FIELD.
WITH ALL OF THE PROGRESS. WE STILL HAVE NOT ACHIEVED
EQUITABLE DECISION MAKING. AS A MEMBER OF THE JPB.
FURTHERMORE, IF SAM TRANS WAS TO GO BANKRUPT AS AN AGENCY
WHAT HAPPENS TO SAN FRANCISCO AND SANTA CLARA?
AS SAM TRANS IS THE MANAGING AGENCY THIS IS VERY
IRRESPONSIBLE TO MANAGE A RAIL SYSTEM LIKE THIS.
AS A RESULT OF THE CONTINUED GOVERNANCE ISSUES I HAVE
INFORMED CALTRAIN AND JPB MEMBERS THAT I WOULD NOT
SUPPORT MEMBER CONTRIBUTIONS FROM SAN FRANCISCO AT THIS TIME
DUE TO THE IRRESPONSIBLE GOVERNANCE STRUCTURE IN PLACE.
>> THE DEFICIT WE HAVE AS A CITY AND THE DEFICIT OF MTA IT
WOULD BE IRRESPONSIBLE FOR US TO USE TAXPAYER DOLLARS TO
SUPPORT A RAIL SYSTEM WHERE WE DO NOT HAVE EQUITABLE DECISION
MAKING AT THE TABLE PARTICULARLY WHEN WE ENSURE THE
PASSAGE OF MEASURE IRR WHICH CONTINUES TO BE A REVENUE
STREAM FOR CALTRAIN. I WANTED TO BRING THIS TO
EVERYONE'S ATTENTION AS I KNOW SOME PEOPLE MAY BE TRYING TO
UNDERMINE MY DECISION NOT TO SUPPORT OUR TAXPAYER MONEY
BEING THROWN AWAY WITHOUT US HAVING PROPER OVERSIGHT TO HOLD
ANYONE ACCOUNTABLE. >> I HAVE ASKED THE JPB TO
CALENDAR AND ENTERTAIN A MOTION AT OUR NEXT MEETING TO ADDRESS
THOSE GOVERNANCE ISSUES SO THAT WE HAVE GUARANTEED OUR
COMMITMENT THAT GOVERNANCE WILL BE ADDRESSED AND THAT WE
GUARANTEE THAT SAN FRANCISCO IS NOT THE BANK FOR A RAIL SYSTEM
THAT WE CANNOT HOLD ACCOUNTABLE.
THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON. SUPERVISOR HUANG.
THANK YOU. BEFORE MENTIONING AN ORDINANCE
RELATED TO STREET TREES AND PUBLIC WORKS, I WANT TO
THANK MY COLLEAGUES FOR EXCUSE ME FOR MY MEDICAL APPOINTMENT
THAT I HAD SCHEDULED WEEKS IN ADVANCE BEFORE I KNEW I'D BE
JOINING THE BOARD AND GIVING ME THAT GRACE.
IT WOULD HAVE BEEN UNFEASIBLE FOR ME TO DELAY AND RESCHEDULE
FOR ANY SYNNEX I WANT TO BE VERY CLEAR THAT MY POSITION ON
THE FAMILY ZONING TIME REMAINS THE SAME.
I WOULD HAVE ALSO VOTED NO ON EXTENDING THE CANNABIS TAX
WAIVER DUE TO BUDGETARY REASONS .
>> I'M PROUD TO CO-SPONSOR AN ORDINANCE WITH MAYOR LARY TO
SIMPLIFY DEVELOPMENT REQUIREMENTS RELATED TO TREE
PLANTING IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> THIS IS PART OF OUR SHARED
COMMITMENT TO MAKING GOVERNMENT EASIER TO NAVIGATE FOR EVERYDAY
SAN FRANCISCANS WHETHER THEY'RE IMPROVING THEIR HOMES, RUNNING
A SMALL BUSINESS OR MAKING ROUTINE CHANGES TO THEIR
PROPERTY CURRENT TREE PLANTING REQUIREMENTS CAN BE OVERLY
COMPLICATED, COSTLY AND TIME CONSUMING FOR PROPERTY OWNERS.
MANY RESIDENTS ESPECIALLY SMALL HOMEOWNERS STRUGGLE WITH THE
PERMITTING STEPS INSPECTION REQUIREMENTS AND COORDINATION
NEEDED TO PLANT A STREET TREE DURING DEVELOPMENT.
THESE CHALLENGES OFTEN CREATE UNNECESSARY DELAYS AND BARRIERS
IN OTHERWISE STRAIGHTFORWARD PROJECTS.
THIS ORDINANCE INTRODUCES A CLEAR AND SIMPLE ALTERNATIVE
AND IN LIEU FEE THAT PROPERTY OWNERS CAN CHOOSE INSTEAD OF
DIRECT TREE PLANTING. THIS OPTION REDUCES PERMITTING
REQUIREMENTS WHILE STILL ENSURING WE ARE FUNDING NEW
TREES THROUGHOUT THE CITY. IT GIVES PUBLIC WORKS THE
ABILITY TO STRATEGICALLY PLANT TREES IN NEIGHBORHOODS WITH
LOWER CANOPY COVERAGE OR GREATER ENVIRONMENTAL NEED.
THE ORDINANCE PROVIDES A FASTER, SIMPLER PATH FOR PEOPLE
TRYING TO MOVE FORWARD WITH IMPROVEMENTS ON THEIR PROPERTY.
IT REDUCES CONFUSION AND COSTS ASSOCIATED WITH NAVIGATING
MULTISTEP PLANTING AND PERMITTING PROCESS.
IT ALSO LINES FOR PRIORITY OF MAKING THE CITY'S REGULATORY
ENVIRONMENT MORE PREDICTABLE, MORE TRANSPARENT AND EASIER FOR
RESIDENTS AND SMALL BUSINESSES. BENEFITS TO THE CITY'S URBAN
FORESTS INCLUDE MAINTAINING AND STRENGTHENING THE CITY'S
COMMITMENT TO EXPANDING THE URBAN TREE CANOPY.
ENSURING THAT EVERY PROJECT STILL CONTRIBUTES TO TREE
PLANTING BUT IN A WAY THAT LETS THE CITY PLANT WHERE TREES ARE
NEEDED MOST. HELPING DIRECT RESOURCES TO
COMMUNITIES WITH FEWER TREES. IMPROVING EQUITY SHARED
ENVIRONMENTAL HEALTH AND NEIGHBORHOOD QUALITY OF
LIFE. THIS FITS OF THE MAYOR'S
SIMPLIFY S.F. INITIATIVE AND REFLECTS THE CITY'S BROADER
PUSH TO REDUCE BUREAUCRACY WHILE MAINTAINING STRONG
ENVIRONMENTAL STANDARDS AND REINFORCES OUR COLLECTIVE
COMMITMENT TO MODERNIZING AND STREAMLINING CITY
PROCESSES. I WANT TO THANK THE MAYOR FOR
PUBLIC WORKS AND OFFICE OF STRATEGIC INITIATIVES FOR THEIR
PARTNERSHIP. THIS LEGISLATION STRIKES THE
RIGHT BALANCE IT SIMPLIFIES EXPERIENCE FOR RESIDENTS WHILE
STRENGTHENING OUR ENVIRONMENTAL STEWARDSHIP CITYWIDE.
>> I THEIR ASSESSMENT. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WONG
SUPERVISOR CHAN. THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES JUST WANT TO REPORT BACK ON MY ROLE FOR THE FREE
CITY COLLEGE OVERSIGHTS COMMITTEE.
WE ARE EVALUATING THROUGH THE SUBCOMMITTEE'S WORK EVALUATING
THE MEMORANDUM OF UNDERSTANDING BETWEEN CITY COLLEGE OF SAN
FRANCISCO AND THE CITY AS WELL AS WITH DCF MAKING SURE WE
MAINTAIN A LEVEL OF SPENDING FOR FREE CITY COLLEGE.
BUT ALSO TO MAKE SURE THAT THERE IS CONTINUING INVESTMENT
AND CLEAR GUIDELINES OF HOW THE CITY WILL FUND A PROGRAM OF
THIS CRITICAL PROGRAM NOT ONLY PROVIDE HIGHER EDUCATION, FREE
HIGHER EDUCATION COURSES FOR OUR HIGH SCHOOL GRADUATES.
IT ALSO PROVIDES FREE WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT AND OTHER TYPES OF
JOB TRAINING FOR THOSE WHO WANT TO SEEK A BETTER JOB OR
ACTUALLY HAVE ADVANCED TRAINING FOR THEIR CURRENT CAREER
AND CONTINUE THEIR CAREER PATH. SO I WILL REPORT BACK ALWAYS
ONCE WE HAVE MORE UPDATES ON THE LANGUAGE AND THE REST I
SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR CHEN. SUPERVISOR CHEN.
SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
>> COLLEAGUES TODAY I WANT TO SHARE THAT I'VE ASKED THE CITY
ATTORNEY TO DRAFT LEGISLATION TO MANDATE A MINIMUM BATHROOM
RATIO IN THE CITY PUBLIC CONVENIENCES LIKE RESTROOMS ARE
ESSENTIAL INFRASTRUCTURE AND AS A CITY THAT PRIDES ITSELF ON
ACCESSIBILITY WE MUST NOT NEGLECT ACCESS TO BATHROOMS.
UNFORTUNATELY, ACCESS TO PUBLICLY ACCESSIBLE BATHROOMS
IS ON THE DECLINE. REMOVING PUBLIC RESTROOMS HURTS
PUBLIC HEALTH, DIGNITY AND URBAN LIFE BY FORCING
PEOPLE TO FIND UNSANITARY ALTERNATIVES CREATING DISEASE
RISKS DISPROPORTIONATELY AFFECTING VULNERABLE
POPULATIONS SUCH AS THE AND HOUSED DISABLED AND THOSE
WITH MEDICAL NEEDS. THE REMOVAL OF PUBLIC RESTROOMS
HAS ALSO CREATED THE UNINTENDED CONSEQUENCE OF INCREASE
IN PUBLIC URINATION AND DEFECATION AND REPORTS OF
FECES IN STREETS OF COURSE. >> A STUDY BY THE UC BERKELEY
SCHOOL OF PUBLIC HEALTH IN 2022 FOUND THAT INCREASED ACCESS TO
PUBLIC TOILETS REDUCED FECES. REPORTS TO THE SAN FRANCISCO
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS. >> A LACK OF BATHROOMS CREATES
SIGNIFICANT BARRIERS FOR ESSENTIAL WORKERS INCLUDING
DELIVERY DRIVERS. OUR MAYORAL CARRIERS AND OUR
TRANSIT OPERATORS. >> THE LACK OF PUBLIC
FACILITIES ALSO AFFECTS OUR TOURISTS TO SAN FRANCISCO, MANY
OF WHOM ARE VISITING SAN FRANCISCO FOR THE FIRST TIME
AND ALSO DESERVE THE CONVENIENCE OF ACCESSIBILITY OF
PUBLIC FACILITIES AS THEY EXPLORE OUR BEAUTIFUL CITY.
I INTEND TO WORK CLOSELY WITH THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS
AND THE COMPTROLLER TO SET ON FEASIBLE AND SUSTAINABLE PLANS
TO ESTABLISH AND MAINTAIN A CITY WIDE PUBLIC BATHROOM
NETWORK AND WOULD INCLUDE BUT NOT BE LIMITED TO THE FIRST OFF
AN INVENTORY OF PUBLIC AND PRIVATE BATHROOMS.
LEGISLATIVE POLICY AND CAPITAL PLANNING STRATEGY
AND COORDINATION WITH PRIVATE ENTITIES OR ADDITIONAL AGENCIES
TO MEET AND MAINTAIN THIS TARGET RATIO.
THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
MR. PRESIDENT, SEEING NO NAMES ON THE ROSTER, THAT CONCLUDES
THE INTRODUCTION OF NEW BUSINESS.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. >> LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT.
ALL RIGHT. FOR THOSE OF YOU IN THE PUBLIC
GALLERY, NOW'S YOUR OPPORTUNITY TO LINE UP ON YOUR RIGHT HAND
SIDE OF THE CHAMBER NEAR THE CURTAINS WHERE YOU MAY SPEAK TO
ITEMS 46 THROUGH 52 THE ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED AND OTHER GENERAL
MATTERS NOT ON THE PUBLISHED AGENDA BUT MUST BE WITHIN THE
BOARD'S SUBJECT MATTER JURISDICTION.
>> SO WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES.
SO WELCOME TO OUR FIRST SPEAKER .
>> LET THERE BE LIGHTS. OKAY I'LL BE LIGHTS.
GENERALLY SPEAKING BUT NO MATTER WHAT NO FEATURE
WHATSOEVER WITHOUT ADDRESSING INSTITUTIONALIZED CHILD
TRAFFICKING. >> SO FORGET YOUR FAKE PAY
ATTENTION TO WHAT SAFETY IS NOT WORKING.
>> IT'S NOT GOING TO WORK. IS THIS THE NBC NEWS NO
NIGHTMARE BEFORE CHRISTMAS? >> YEAH, THAT'S WHERE IT STANDS
FOR NBC. >> SO GO BACK TO THE MOVIES YOU
ANYONE KNOWS THAT THE NIGHTMARE BEFORE CHRISTMAS WAS ENTIRELY
SHOT ON NINE STREETS AT FOLSOM. I WAS ON ITS I WORKED FOR
MONTHS ON THIS AMAZING STOP MOTION ANIMATION MASTERPIECE.
WE STEAM THEN COMING OVER I WAS 22 SELECTED BY THE DEPARTMENTS
I MEAN WHY SHOULD I BE SO SIZED SELECTED BY THE DEPARTMENT FOR
ADDICTION FROM SIXTH WHEN I WAS A STUDENT IN A FILM PRODUCTION
. SO MY SHORT FILM WAS SELECTED
SAID YEAH THIS GUY WE NEED HIM SO FOUR MONTHS A YEAR BASICALLY
BUT HE'S AN ASSISTANT TRAINEE. >> AWESOME.
THE TIME OF MY LIFE AS FAR AS THE GENIUS I WAS WORKING WITH.
YEAH. >> SO SO TIM BURTON WAS COMING
ONLY TWICE I SAW HIM TWICE HE WAS SHOOTING THE FIRST BATMAN
AT THE TIME 1991 YOU KNOW IS NICHOLSON ON THE DIGITAL OKAY
LONG STORY SHELF. SO WHAT I MEAN IS THAT YOU GUYS
MUST ASK FOR A PLEDGE TO BE PUT ON THIS BUILDING HERE WAS SHUT
THE WORLDWIDE NON STOP MOTION ANIMATION FEATURE CALLED THE
NIGHTMARE BEFORE CHRISTMAS YOU USED IT ENOUGH, RIGHT?
NIGHTMARE BEFORE CHRISTMAS. SPOOKY.
SO NOW A MERRY CHRISTMAS. IT'S MY LAST TIME COMING HERE
FOR THE EVERYTHING WILL STOP NEXT YEAR BECAUSE NOW I MEAN
GIVE US A BREAK NO MATTER WHAT YOU NEED TO ADDRESS THIS
OTHERWISE I MEAN, YOU GUYS YOUR INTELLIGENCE IS AT PAUL THANK
YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. LET'S WELCOME OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. OKAY.
BEFORE I BEGIN TO READ ITEM NUMBER 44 APRIL 22ND 2025 THERE
AT THE SANTA CLARA COUNTY BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
I'D LIKE TO JUST TAKE A QUICK SURVEY.
HOW MANY OF YOU HEARD HARRISON FORD INTERVIEW PATRICK BYRNE?
CAN WE SEE HER SHOW TODAY LIVE ?
CAN WE SEE A SHOW OF HANDS IN THAT PLEASE?
UP, UP, UP, UP, UP. >> MARK, THIS IS YOUR TIME.
OKAY. THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
YOU MAY PUT YOUR HANDS DOWN AND THEN REAL QUICK, HOW MANY
CHOSE NOT TO PARTICIPATE IN THE FIRST SURVEY?
>> UP, UP, UP, UP, UP. >> MM HMM.
OKAY. YOU MAY PUT YOUR HANDS DOWN.
THAT THREW SOMETHING INTO THE MIX, DOESN'T IT?
HMM. SO IN OTHER WORDS, SOME OF YOU
CHOSE NOT TO PARTICIPATE IN THE FIRST SURVEY, RIGHT?
>> HUH? >> OKAY, NOW BEFORE I BEGIN TO
READ ITEM 40 I JUST LIKE TO SAY I WAS CHILLING OUT IN THE
LIVING ROOM AND WITH MY WIFE AND YOU KNOW, SHE SITTING ON
THE RECLINER THERE HAVING A COLD BEER AND SHE WALKED OVER
TO ME AND TOOK HER BLOUSE OFF AND HER BRA OFF.
AND AS I BEGAN TO FONDLE HER I SAID, YOU KNOW, HONEY, I SHOULD
BE KILLED FOR THIS IF WE WERE NOT MARRIED.
>> MARK, THIS IS AN APPROPRIATE FOR THIS MEETING NOW YOU FOLKS
ARE SAYING THAT TWO GUYS CAN MARRY AND TWO WOMEN CAN MARRY
AND IT'S NOT SINFUL. IT'S NOT WRONG, BUT YOU'RE
WRONG, KAY GOD IS THE AUTHORITY.
KAY AND GOD MADE MARRIAGE AND GOD SAID THE MARRIAGE BED
IS UNDEFILED MONGERS AND ADULTERERS.
>> GOD WILL JUDGE OKAY, ADOPT A RESOLUTION REPEALING RESOLUTION
NUMBER BIO OS WHICH AUTHORIZES THE COUNTY EXECUTIVE OR
DESIGNEE TO DECLINE TO APPROVE EXPENDITURES OF COUNTY FUNDS
AND TRAVEL TO STATES THAT ENACT LAWS AGAINST THE LGBT
REAFFIRMING THE COUNTY'S UNWAVERING COMMITMENT TO
SUPPORTING AND HONORING THE LGBT.
>> THIS IS A SIN WE SHOULD NOT HONOR THE LGBT MARKER.
>> YOUR TIME'S EXPIRED. CAN WE HEAR FROM THE NEXT
SPEAKER PLEASE? >> MR..
MR. DE COSTA WELCOME FOLKS FOR JESUS SUPERVISORS THREE
INNOCENT HARDWORKING EMPLOYEES FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC
UTILITIES COMMISSION WERE DISMISSED.
THEY WERE DISMISSED BECAUSE THEY WERE ENTICED TO WORK ON A
PROJECT IT'S CALLED CONFINED SPACE CLEANING THE RESERVOIR
40FT 50FT BELOW WITH NO TRAINING, NO CERTIFICATION
WHATSOEVER. SO WHEN THEY BROUGHT THIS
MATTER TO THE MANAGER HOURS, THE MANAGERS INSTEAD OF
LISTENING TO THEM AND PUTTING THEIR THINGS IN ORDER
TERMINATED THEM THE LAST THREE SIPC MEETINGS I HAVE BROUGHT
THIS MATTER TO THE COMMISSIONERS AND NOW I'M
BRINGING IT TO YOUR ATTENTION THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS JUST READ THE POLICIES AND STANDARD OPERATING
PROCEDURES FOR THOSE WORKERS WHO WORK UNDER THOSE PROJECTS.
SO CONFINED SPACE FOR THIS TREE WORKER SHOULD BE GIVEN A CHANCE
TO WORK FOR THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO ONE WORK FOR
EIGHT YEARS, ONE WORK FOR SIX YEARS AND ONE WORK FOR THREE
MONTHS. BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IS LET'S
NOT JUST TALK ABOUT SAFETY. LET'S DO SOMETHING ABOUT IT
AND CALL UPON DENNIS HERRERA TO DO THE RIGHT THING.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THANK YOU, FRANCISCO ACOSTA FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
GOOD AFTERNOON, PRESIDENT BENJAMIN SUPERVISORS MADAM
CLERK. MY NAME IS ANTONIO THE YES
AND I'M WITH PAULETTE. I'M THE ORGANIZATION'S DIRECTOR
. >> I'M HERE TO SPEAK ABOUT ITEM
NUMBER 47 THE RESOLUTION AFFIRMING SAN FRANCISCO'S
COMMITMENT TO DECARBONIZATION EFFORTS THAT CENTER
ENVIRONMENTAL JUSTICE. FIRST OF ALL, I WANT TO THANK
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FOR HER LEADERSHIP ON THIS ISSUE
AND SUPERVISORS MELGAR, CHIEN MAHMOOD AND FIELDER FOR
SPONSORING THE RESOLUTION THAT HAS FOR 35 YEARS ORGANIZED FOR
HEALTHY THRIVING COMMUNITIES. MORE RECENTLY A FOCUS OF OUR
WORK HAS BEEN ADVANCING HEALTHY RESILIENT HOMES TO EQUITABLE
BUILDING DECARBONIZATION. WE HAVE BEEN DOING THIS WORK
IN COLLABORATION WITH CITY DEPARTMENTS ESPECIALLY THE SAN
FRANCISCO ENVIRONMENT DEPARTMENT VARIOUS CBOS SUCH AS
BABY 100 POINT COMMUNITY ADVOCATES SOUTH OF MARKET
COMMUNITY ACTION NETWORK, THE EMERALD CITIES COLLABORATIVE
NORTHERN CALIFORNIA AND MANY OTHERS TO THE CLIMATE EQUITY
HUB SAN FRANCISCO'S CLIMATE ACTION HUB AND HAVE DEEPLY
APPRECIATED THAT COLLABORATION TO ADVANCE BUILDING
DECARBONIZATION IN AN EQUITABLE MANNER.
>> I'M HERE TO JUST ASK THAT THE BOARD VOTE IN SUPPORT OF
THIS RESOLUTION ADOPT THIS RESOLUTION AND STATE THE CITY'S
SUPPORT AND AFFIRMING OF THIS THIS WORK AND ENHANCING IT IN A
MANNER THAT MEETS THE NEEDS OF ESPECIALLY LOW INCOME AND THIS
SIMPLE WISE RESIDENTS OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THANK YOU, ANTONIO DIAZ FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. ALL RIGHT.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> ALL RIGHT.
COME ON. >> COME ON UP.
>> GOOD EVENING. WHAT ARE SUPERVISORS HERE?
>> MY NAME IS RICHARD SD PETERSON.
I JUST WANTED TO COMMENT ON THE PAPER TODAY THAT EVERYBODY HAS
PROBABLY SEEN. AND IT'S CURIOUS THE
JUXTAPOSING ATION OF THE SPENDING BY CITY ON NONPROFITS
DOUBLE A'S AND YET THE PARCEL TAX IS AT THE AT THE SAME
IN THE SAME COLUMN AND GIVING US AN IDEA OF WHAT IT'S GOING
TO COST FOR PARCEL TAXES IN THAT PARCEL TAX THEN I THINK
THAT THE THE CHANGE IN POWER IS MOVING FROM DOWNTOWN TO THE
WEST SIDE IN DISTRICT ONE AND DISTRICT SIX AND YOU WILL
SOON SEE IN THE SEE THE POWER OF THE WEST SIDE BECAUSE I
THINK THE WEST SIDE HAS MORE TAXABLE OR TAXABLE PROPERTIES
ON PARCELS THAN DOES DOWNTOWN. I DON'T THINK THAT WE SHOULD
WORRY ABOUT NORTH BEACH. I THINK NORTH BEACH IS ALREADY
WELL SERVICED BY OUR PAST SUPERVISOR PESKIN.
>> THANK YOU AND HAVE A GOOD CHRISTMAS.
>> THANK YOU. RICHARD PEARSON FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> HI MY NAME'S BRIAN STORE.
I'M HERE TO TALK ABOUT THE GENESIS L ROADS.
SO THE SECOND TIME I'VE BEEN HERE I'VE BEEN HERE WITH FORCE
AND AUTO TRACKED BY GENESIS L RAD MODEL 915 X T'S IN THIS
BUILDING. THIS IS LIKE THE FIFTH TIME I'M
PICKING THEM UP ON TO INFRASOUND RECORDERS RIGHT NOW
ALL ROADS IN SAN FRANCISCO THAT CAN HIT THE CITY SHOULD HAVE
FEDERAL COMPLIANCE CHECKS ON THEM TO MAKE SURE THAT THEY'RE
BEING OPERATED LEGALLY FOR FEDERAL, STATE AND LOCAL LAWS.
THEY'RE BEING USED AS MILITARY WEAPONS.
THAT'S WHAT THE SUPREME COURT'S RULED.
HAMAS IS A MILITARY WEAPON. IT'S AN ACOUSTIC WEAPON.
THE NEAREST COVERAGE AREA IS DOWN HERE AT THE BOTTOM OF THE
GOLDEN GATE BRIDGE. AND SO IT'S A SERIOUS PROBLEM.
THE FIX TO IT IS COMPLIANCE CHECKS.
I'VE MADE TWO POLICE REPORTS WITH THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE
DEPARTMENT. I'VE MET WITH THE FBI HERE
AND THE SAME THING'S STILL HAPPENING.
AND EVERY TIME I COME TO SAN FRANCISCO IS ALL ROADS ARE
DANGEROUS, OPERATORS ARE DANGEROUS CRIMINALS AND WHERE
THEY CAN CONTROL AN EL RAD PEOPLE'S LIVES ARE IN DANGER.
THEY HAVE COMMITTED ABOUT EVERY KIND POSSIBLE ON OUR ROADS.
I'VE BEEN HIT IN AUTO TRACKED BY THE MILITARY WEAPONS WHICH
THE EL REDS ARE LIKE I SAID OVER FIVE TIMES IN THIS
BUILDING AND I HAVE TWO IPHONES WITH EVERY SOUND EVIDENCE TO
PROVE THIS. SO IT PICKS UP THE LOW
FREQUENCY THAT'S INAUDIBLE TO OUR EARS AND THEN THE PARTICLES
THAT THE ACOUSTIC WEAPONS USE TO PUSH THE SOUND.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME. THANK YOU BRIAN STORE FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. WELCOME.
MY NAME IS SALAH HAPPIER CHANDLER AND I'M HERE
IN REGARDS TO THE DEBRIS AND THE FILTH THAT'S IN BAYVIEW
YOU SHOULD HAVE SEEN ON CARROLL STREET NEAR CANDLESTICK SOMEONE
CAME WITH THE MULTIPLE TRUCK AND DROPPED TONS AND TONS
AND TONS AND TONS OF TRASH. THEY HAD TO BRING A TRUCKLOAD
TO COME AND PICK IT UP ALMOST ON EVERY CORNER AND BAYVIEW IS
NOTHING BUT FILTH AND WHEN THE IMMIGRANTS CAME DURING THE 20
CULVERT 2020 CULVERT AND IT WAS ALLOWED IN THE CITY FOR ALL OF
THE TENTS TO BE SET UP AND BILL AND CARDBOARDS AND FILTH
AND ROACHES AND RATS WHERE WE USED TO GO AND SIT BY THE WATER
BY CANDLESTICK WE CAN'T DO THAT ANYMORE BECAUSE IT WAS CLOSED
DOWN WHICH SUCH FILTH FILTHINESS IT IS NO WAY NO WISE
THAT ANY DISTRICT YOU WOULD ALLOW THIS FOR THE PACIFIC THE
MARINA TWIN PEAKS ANY OF WHAT'S BEING ALLOWED DR. ESPANOLA
JACKSON TOLD ME SHE SAID CONCERNING ALL OF THE TRUCKING
INDUSTRY THAT'S OVER IN BAYVIEW THAT TEXAS SHOULD BE ADDED FOR
US IN THE RESIDENTIAL AREA WE'RE THE ONLY NATION OF PEOPLE
THE BLACK PEOPLE THAT DON'T HAVE NO OWNERSHIP, NO NOTHING
IN THE MASS COLLECT COLLECTIVE EVERY NATION ARE PROGRESSING
BUT THE AFRICAN-AMERICAN PEOPLE WE HAVE NO REPRESENTATIVE YOU
SEE WHAT'S HAPPENING CONCERNING SOMALIA AND THE REPRESENTATION
IF IT'S GOOD OR IF IT'S BAD THERE THERE'S SOMEONE
IN CONGRESS FOR THE SOMALIANS SAN FRANCISCO AS A SANCTUARY
FOR THE IMMIGRANTS ALL OVER THE WORLD EVERY NATION IS
REPRESENTED BUT THE BLACK NATION THE POLITICIANS CAN ONLY
SPEAK FOR THEIR DISTRICT BUT THERE THERE'S NO ONE TO
REPRESENT MY PEOPLE AND THIS IS THE REASON WHY WE ARE IN THE
CONDITION. WHEN YOU TALK ABOUT SNAP YOU
YOU TALK ABOUT SECTION EIGHT YOU ALL OF THE DISENFRANCHIZED
BUT NOT ONE PART OF THE OKAY. >> THANK YOU.
MISS CHANDLER, PLEASE. THANK YOU MISS CHANDLER.
BE THAT AND CONTINUE THIS CONVERSATION.
>> OH, THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER WELCOME. HELLO.
THE BUREAU DUFFY HEY, THAT SOUNDS GOOD.
UH, DISTRICT FIVE UH, I JUST WANTED TO CONGRATULATE THEIR
NEWEST MEMBER WHO SITS NEAREST TO THE PUBLIC COMMENT HAVING
SURVIVED ONE, I HOPE THE HEALTH CARE TREATED YOU WELL AND YOU
WERE ABLE TO GET THROUGH IT. THERE ARE OFTEN COMMENTS THAT
ARE A LITTLE BIT MISGUIDED BUT WE GET TO HEAR FROM THE COMMON
PEOPLE BUSINESS PEOPLE I SUPPOSE THE COOLEST ONE I EVER
WAS WITH WHEN WHEN GEORGE SHULTZ WAS UP HERE HOUSE WAS
MEMORABLE. I REMEMBER JOHN BARTELS USED TO
COME IN HERE LONG AFTER HE WAS A SUPERVISOR AND WELCOME.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
>> ALL RIGHT. LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER. >> WELCOME.
HI. MY NAME IS ALEX NICHOLAS.
>> I HONESTLY JUST WANT TO SAY THANK YOU.
WHAT YOU GUYS DO AS REPRESENTATIVES IS SOMETHING I
CARE PASSIONATELY ABOUT. I THINK THAT NEXT YEAR IS GOING
TO BE A FUN YEAR. I THINK THERE'S GOING TO BE UPS
AND DOWNS AND I'D REALLY LIKE TO SUPPORT A CONTINGENCY PLAN
AS CHANGES HAPPEN AND THEY RISE AND OCCUR AND THEY'LL BE
DIFFICULT AND MAYBE THEY'LL BE EXCITING BUT I THINK THAT THERE
NEEDS TO BE MORE COMMUNITY REPRESENTATION ESPECIALLY WITH
THE YOUNGER GENERATION ON WHAT IT'S LIKE TO SURVIVE THINGS
THAT WE MAYBE DON'T UNDERSTAND OR HAVE CONTROL OVER THAT YOU
AS REPRESENTATIVES ARE REALLY MANAGING FOR THE PEOPLE OF THIS
CITY. SO MOSTLY JUST THANK YOU AND I
LOOK FORWARD TO LIVING THE GOOD LIFE HERE IN THE CITY WITH OUR
WONDERFUL SUPPORT WORK. >> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF
THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD DURING
GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT? THIS IS YOUR OPPORTUNITY.
>> PLEASE COME FORWARD. MR. PRESIDENT.
ALL RIGHT. PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED.
>> MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR FOUR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE AGENDA ITEMS 46 THROUGH 52 ITEMS 46 THROUGH 52
WERE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION BUT WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE
. A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED
FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON FIRST APPEARANCE TODAY.
ALTERNATIVELY, A MEMBER MAY REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST
APPEARANCE TO GO TO COMMITTEE. >> I WOULD LIKE TO SEVEN ITEM
48 MADAM CLERK. >> IT'S 48, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> YEP. OKAY, MA'AM.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR, I WOULD LIKE TO SET FOR 49 AND 52 PLEASE.
>> SUPERVISOR WONG SWAN AND MAKE SURE MY NAME IS ADDED
TO ITEM 46. >> DR. ZANG DO YOU GOT THAT,
MADAM CLERK? YES.
>> YES. OKAY.
THEN COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE REMAINING BALANCE
OF THE ITEMS ON ITEMS 46 4750 AND 51.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I
AMENDMENT I SUPERVISOR MILKER I MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN ABSENT SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED MADAM CLERK CAN YOU
PLEASE CALL ITEM 48 ITEM 48 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO
RECOGNIZE DECEMBER 12TH 2025 AS DRAG STORY HOUR DAY IN THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO COLLEAGUES THIS ITEM RECOGNIZES
AS OUR CLERK INDICATED DECEMBER 12TH 2014 FIVE AS DRAG STORY
HOUR DAY DRAG STORY HOUR WAS FOUNDED RIGHT HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO IN 2015. >> IT WAS STARTED BY AUTHOR
MICHELLE TEA, VIRGIE TOVAR AND JULIAN DELGADO LA PARRA
AND THE FIRST PERFORMANCE FEATURED ARE NOW SAN FRANCISCO
DRAG LAUREATE PATRICIA AT THE HARVEY MILK MEMORIAL BRANCH
LIBRARY DRAG STORY HOUR CREATE SPACE FOR ROLE MODELS
AND CHILDREN'S STORIES AND TEACHES KIDS THAT
AUTHENTICITY AND INDIVIDUALITY SHOULD BE CELEBRATED.
IT'S GROWN INTO AN INTERNATIONAL MOVEMENT REACHING
THOUSANDS OF KIDS AND FAMILIES AROUND THE WORLD.
SAN FRANCISCO HAS ALWAYS BEEN A CITY THAT CHAMPIONS CREATIVITY
AND LGBTQ VISIBILITY AND DRAG STORY HOUR EMBODIES BOTH THIS
RESOLUTION CELEBRATES A REMARKABLE MILESTONE
AND DEMONSTRATES OUR CONTINUED SUPPORT FOR PROGRAMS THAT LIFT
UP CHILDREN, AFFIRM DIVERSE IDENTITIES AND INSPIRE ALL OF
US TO EMBRACE OUR FULLEST, MOST AUTHENTIC SELVES.
AND I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR HER CO-SPONSORSHIP OF
THIS AND I THINK WE CAN PROBABLY TAKE THIS ITEM.
>> SAME HOUSE. OH NO, MR. PRESIDENT.
WE HAVE A NEW HOUSE. WE HAVE A NEW HOUSE.
>> YES, MADAM CLERK LET'S CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 40 EIGHT
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
MIDDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR FOR SADR
SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EITHER ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEM 49 ITEM 49 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO URGE STATE
OFFICIALS TO AMEND THE HOUSING CRISIS ACT OF 2019 OR SENATE
BILL 330 INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO GOVERNMENT CODE
SECTIONS 65941.1 66 300 AND 66301 THAT LIMITED SAN
FRANCISCO'S ABILITY TO PROTECT RENT CONTROLLED UNITS FROM
DEMOLITION, WEAKEN TENANTS RIGHTS OF RETURN AFTER
DEMOLITION OR REDEVELOPMENT AND UNDERMINED LOCAL HOUSING
ELEMENT OBJECTIVES TO PRESERVE AFFORDABLE HOUSING, SUPERVISES
MELGAR THANK YOU COLLEAGUES ARE HAVE A SMALL TECHNICAL
AMENDMENT FOR THIS RESOLUTION FOR CLARITY WHICH I DISTRIBUTED
AND IT IS TO ADD THE PHRASE SECTIONS ENACTED BY THE PASSAGE
OF TWO PAGE ONE LINE THREE AND PAGE THREE, LINE FOUR
AND THAT'S IT. ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR CONSIDERATION.
>> TAKE THAT AS A MOTION TO AMEND AND IT'S BEEN SECONDED BY
SUPERVISOR WALTON AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT MOTION WITHOUT
OBJECTION AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THE AMENDED ITEM SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE AMENDED
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE
CALL ITEM 52? >> ITEM 52 THIS IS A MOTION TO
ESTABLISH THE 2026 BOARD OF SUPERVISORS REGULAR MEETING
SCHEDULE PURSUANT TO THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS RULES OF ORDER
SECTION 4.2 AND 4.2.1 BY CANCELING THE REGULAR BOARD
MEETINGS OF JANUARY 20TH FEBRUARY 17TH MAY 26TH
SEPTEMBER 8TH, OCTOBER 13TH AND DECEMBER ONE AND ALL
REGULAR BOARD AND COMMITTEE MEETINGS DURING THE SPRING,
SUMMER AND WINTER BREAKS BEGINNING MARCH 30TH THROUGH
APRIL 3RD 2026 RETURNING ON APRIL 6TH 2026 AND BEGINNING
AUGUST 3RD THROUGH AUGUST 28TH 2026 RETURNING ON AUGUST 31ST
2026 AND BEGINNING DECEMBER 16TH 2026 THROUGH JANUARY 7TH
2027 TO RETURN ON JANUARY 8TH 2027 AND FURTHER TO SUSPEND
PORTIONS OF THE BOARD RULE 4.2 TO EFFECTUATE CERTAIN DATES
WITHIN THE REGULAR MEETING SCHEDULE TO AUGMENT THE FLOW OF
BUSINESS SUPERVISES MELGAR THANK YOU SO MUCH.
FIRST I WANT TO SAY THANK YOU MADAM CLERK FOR ALL THE WORK
THAT GOES INTO PREPARING THIS AND PUTTING IT OUT.
I WOULD LIKE TO MAKE A MOTION TO AMEND THIS MOTION SO THAT WE
CANCEL THE BOARD MEETING HERE THE WEEK OF THANKSGIVING
AND 2026 LIKE WE DID THIS YEAR LIKE WE DID FOR THE PAST COUPLE
OF YEARS SO THAT WE DO NOT MEET THAT WEEK IN AND SET WE MEET
THE FOLLOWING WEEK. >> THIS ALIGNS WITH THE SCHOOL
DISTRICT'S HOLIDAY SCHEDULE FOR THOSE OF US WHO HAVE KIDS
IN THE PUBLIC SCHOOL DISTRICT AND THEY WILL BE OFF THAT WEEK.
THIS AMENDMENT OR THE AMENDMENTS ARE ON PAGE ONE LINE
SIX IN THE LONG TITLED DELETING DECEMBER 1ST AND REPLACING IT
WITH NOVEMBER 24TH. AND ON PAGE TWO LINE SEVEN TO
DELETE DECEMBER 1ST AND REPLACE IT WITH NOVEMBER 24TH ON PAGE
TWO LINES EIGHT THROUGH 11 I WOULD LIKE TO ADD A CLAUSE TO
SUSPEND A PORTION OF BOARD RULE 4.2 THAT REQUIRES THAT THE
BOARD MEET DURING THE WEEK OF THANKSGIVING, CANCEL THE
MEETING ON NOVEMBER 24TH TO OBSERVE THE THANKSGIVING
HOLIDAY DURING THE WEEK OF THANKSGIVING AND SCHEDULE A
BOARD TO MEET ON DECEMBER 1ST. >> THANK YOU COLLEAGUES FOR
YOUR CONSIDERATION. >> IS THERE A SECOND FOR THAT
MOTION SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR CHAN?
>> IS THERE ANY DISCUSSION OF THE MOTION?
SEEING NONE. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT MOTION
WITHOUT OBJECTION. THE MOTION PASSES.
AND THEN I THINK WE CAN TAKE THE AMENDED ITEM SAME SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT WITHOUT OBJECTION THE AMENDED
MOTION IS APPROVED. >> OKAY, MADAM CLERK, DO WE
HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS?
I HAVE NONE TO REPORT. MR. PRESIDENT, WOULD YOU PLEASE
READ THE IN MEMORIAM? >> YESTERDAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUAL.
ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR WALTON, SUPERVISOR FIELDER REQUESTED BY
SUPERVISOR WALTON TO BE ON BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS FOR THE CHERISHED GENERAL HOSPITAL AND UCSF
SOCIAL WORKER MR. ALBERTO RANGEL.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. AND I THINK THAT BRINGS US TO
THE END OF OUR AGENDA DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER BUSINESS
BEFORE US TODAY? >> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS
FOR TODAY. THEN WE ARE ADJOURNED.
>>